So, John, was Jeffrey Epstein part of
the US government or a foreign
government that they used for
blackmailing people?
>> Jeffrey Epstein was a Mossad access
agent. Do you think we'll ever see the
list? That's really the question. The
Israelis, they are not permitted in CIA
headquarters because every time they
would come, they would give us gifts.
And the gifts always had listening
devices embedded in them with batteries.
The CIA is made up of thousands of
people who will break every law, lie to
the congressional overseers, overthrow
governments, murder innocents, knowing
that they could get away with it.
>> What traits are they looking for?
>> They are looking for people who have
sociopathic tendencies, not sociopaths.
So, there are enhanced interrogation
techniques, but then you get into things
like strip the guy naked, chain him to
an eyebolt in the ceiling, chill the
cell to 50° Fahrenheit, and then throw a
bucket of ice water on him every hour.
We prisoners with that technique.
>> Talking to you, the truth is really
important to you.
>> Oh my god. There's nothing as important
as the truth. Nothing. Even when it's a
hideous truth.
[Music]
So, John, was Jeffrey Epstein
part of the US government or a foreign
government that they used for
blackmailing people?
>> I I'll start off by saying I have no
proof
of my position. Uh but
I feel very very confident that Jeffrey
Epstein was a Mossad, what we would call
an access agent. Um an access agent is
somebody who gives a a foreign
intelligence service or any intelligence
service access to targets that they
otherwise wouldn't have access to. For
example, if you are a foreign
intelligence service and you want to
know what Bill Clinton says about an
issue or Prince Andrew or Bill Gates or
anybody else that went to Epstein
Island, you're not going to be able to
recruit Bill Clinton. He's not
recruitable or Bill Gates. So, you do
the next best thing. You recruit someone
who has regular easy access to them. And
then if there's a little blackmail
thrown in at the same time, it makes the
quality of your of your information that
much better. Otherwise, why would
Jeffrey Epstein
have audio and video in every literally
every single room of his house,
including the bathrooms? Why? For what?
Who does that?
>> Nobody.
>> And another thing is, where did his
money come from? I mean, there were
these allegations in Vanity Fair that he
was in some sort of gay relationship
with Les Wexner, the Ohio billionaire.
Um, and Less Wexner gave millions and
millions of dollars to be his tax
advisor. Less Wexner says that that's
not true. Less Wexner's wife says that
that's not true. So, that money had to
come from somewhere. I believe that he
was working for the Israelis. Do you
think he's still alive?
>> No, I don't. I think he's dead. Do you
think we'll ever see the list?
Uh, that's really the question.
You know, the black books are out there.
One of them was offered for sale at
Alexander Auctions. It's a Maryland
auction house, and it did not meet its
reserve price of $100,000 about six
weeks ago. So, the books are out there.
The names in the books are out there,
but not all those names necessarily, you
know, were doing anything illegal or
inappropriate. The lists lists, you
know, in a perfect world, sure, yes, the
Justice Department would make them
available or an enterprising
investigative journalist would file a
Freedom of Information Act request and
he would make them or she would make
them available. But we haven't gotten
there yet. I I I really do believe maybe
naively that eventually we will see
those lists, but I don't think
>> not anytime in the future.
>> Not anytime soon.
>> John, throughout your career at the CIA,
did you ever come close to getting
assassinated or getting taught?
>> Oh, twice.
Close. Close. Uh the first time was in
um in Athens in 2000. I was I was
stationed in Athens as the
counterterrorism
um center representative
and I was there specifically
to work against a group called
revolutionary organization 17 November.
We called it 17 November
17N.
Um there were others popular
revolutionary struggle and then all the
Arabs had a presence there. the Popular
Front for the liberation of Palestine,
the PFLP General Command, the Democratic
Front for the Liberation of Palestine,
Abu Nidal, the Libyans, everybody was
there, bombs going off all the time. But
specifically, we were there for 17
November because they had murdered the
CIA station chief, two uh DoD defense
ataches. Uh they had shot and killed uh
a US Air Force tech sergeant. Poor guy
was just doing his laundry in the
basement of his apartment building. They
blew his brains out. Um, they killed the
Turkish ambassador, the Turkish deputy
ambassador. They killed the uh the
minister of communications, the minister
of finance, the governor of the central
bank, the the prime minister's
son-in-law. Very, very deadly group. So,
I was very, very careful about my own
security. I was I took surveillance and
surveillance detection so seriously that
the CIA made me a surveillance
instructor after I got back from uh well
after I got back from Pakistan a couple
of years later. But anyway, this was a
group that was so deadly they had
murdered 28 people. They had wounded
hundreds.
And not only had they never been caught,
we were never able to identify a single
one of them. They would do these they
would do these assassinations in broad
daylight in front of 2,000 people and
nobody saw a thing because they were so
petrified of being the next victim. And
even the Greek media called them the
phantom organization because nobody ever
saw anything.
So as a CIA officer, I drove a fully
armored BMW 540. It was the first 540 in
Greece. As a matter of fact, we we
couldn't even insure it because there
were no other 540s. We had to insure it
through a company in Germany and and I
was always heavily armed. We all were. I
had a 9mm and a tear away fanny pack on
my waist. I had a 38 snubnse on my
ankle. And then just in case things
really went to [__] I had a buck knife
in my back pocket.
So
every day, and this is what we're all
trained to do, every day you leave your
house at a different time and you take a
different route to work every single day
because as soon as you establish a
pattern, they know where to be standing
to kill you as you go through that
intersection.
So the British embassy in uh oh I guess
it was February or March of 2000 got a
new defense attache Steven Saunders and
Steven moved in next door to me. Our our
backyards abudded
and he was just such a lovely guy. He
was the life of the party. We used to
joke that he was a media [__] because
anytime anybody had a camera, he would
run right up to it and, you know,
laughing and drinking and he was at
every party and he's on TV all the time
and he's being interviewed in the papers
all the time. He's everywhere.
So in early April of 2000, we're at a
dinner party and I was standing with
Steve and with the French defense ates
and the American defense attaches
and he was making fun of me because I
had just gotten my BMW.
And he said, "You Americans are so
paranoid about security." He goes, "This
is an EU country. It's a NATO country.
what are you so afraid of? And they all
chuckle. And I said, you Brits live in a
dream world. If you think that because
they have palm trees and pretty beaches
that they're not going to kill you if
they have the chance. If they have the
chance, they're going to kill you. We
all laughed again. Two weeks later, I
did something that I had never done
before. I slept through my alarm. And I
woke up and I looked at the clock and I
was like, "Oh my god, I slept in." Which
meant I didn't have time to do this
two-hour surveillance detection route. I
just had to get on the main road, go
straight to the embassy. Now, I lived in
a northern suburb called Geisia. And the
main boulevard is like, let me think, 12
lanes.
Goes directly from the northern suburbs
directly to the American Embassy and
then to the British embassy. No turns
straight down the mountain and it
changes names when once you hit the
Athens city limit it it becomes uh uh
let's see Queen Sophia Street. I said
damn it I I have to get on on the road
and just go straight in. So I get in the
car. I get on QVCs. It's a parking lot.
And I I was like great. Now what am I
going to say when I get there two hours
late? Right. And the thing with GVCS is
it had these concrete jersey barriers.
So once you were on, you were on.
>> You're not getting back off.
>> Can't get back off.
>> So I'm inching, like literally inching.
And then I did something else that I
never did. I turned the radio on because
in training they tell us never ever play
the radio because you don't want to be
distracted. You know, you're humming
some song looking this into space and
the assassin's coming up on your side,
you know, with a an armor-piercing, you
know, round or something.
So I turn the radio on and the the DJ is
saying uh avoid Kicas Boulevard. There
was a traffic incident at Felith. Felith
is the halfway point between Kisia and
the embassy. I was like dang it five
miles I have of this.
So I'm inching down the mountain and
then a half an hour later he says avoid
GCS Boulevard. There was a criminal
incident at Felith and I thought, "Huh,
I never heard that before. I wonder what
kind of criminal incident at nine
o'clock in the morning would jam up
traffic like this." And still inching
down the mountain. Another half hour
passes and the guy says, "Avoid GCS
Boulevard. There was a terrorist attack
at Filoth." Well, I definitely had never
heard that before. And he says it just
as I'm approaching this white rover in
the left lane and the cops are putting
tape around it and I saw the license
plate. Now Athens was so it well was
back then so dangerous for Americans. We
spent more money on security in Athens
than we did in Beirut. That's how
dangerous it was because of this group.
So we didn't have diplomatic license
plates. It was too dangerous. It would
it would allow them to more easily
identify us as Americans. But the
Greeks, in their infinite wisdom,
gave literally everybody in the American
embassy license plates that began with
YHB.
Everybody. It was worse than a
diplomatic plate
>> cuz you knew.
>> Yeah. My mine was YHB1 1442. I still
remember it after 25 years. My wife was
YHB 1367.
So I look at this license plate on this
rover and it's YBH
and four numbers. And I thought, "Oh no,
they killed some poor Greek thinking
that it was one of us." And then I
remember, "No, the British embassy is
YBH
and Steve Saunders drives a white
rover." So I called the station and my
boss says, "Where are you?" I said, "I'm
stuck on f on uh KCS Boulevard, but I
think Steven Saunders was just
assassinated." He said, "Why? What do
you see?" And I I told him, you know,
it's the white rover. I said, "It's just
soaked. The interior's soaked in blood."
and the driver side windows shot out and
he said, "Okay, get here as quickly as
you can." So, just as I get past the
car, of course, traffic opens up. I run
into the station. Everybody's waiting
for me. So, I told him what happened. My
boss picks up the phone. He calls the
British embassy and this the British the
MI6 secretary answers and uh and he
says, "We think Steven Saunders was just
assassinated." And it's like she didn't
like it didn't register or or she
misheard. And she says, "I'm sorry.
Steven's not in yet today." And he said,
"No, you're not listening to me. We
think Steven was just assassinated." And
she says, "Oh, oh my god, we'll call you
right back." And then she called us back
20 minutes later and she said he had
just died at the Red Cross hospital,
which ironically is next door to the
British Embassy. So several months
passed. Now what 17 November used to do
is they would drop a manifesto. This was
a this was a an incredibly violent
Marxist Leninist um group. They would
drop a manifesto at the site of the hit
or they would put a manifesto in a
garbage can somewhere in the
neighborhood and then call a leftist
newspaper to tell them where the the
garbage can was that they could go
retrieve it. But they didn't leave a
manifesto with him.
They had done that once or twice before,
but it was unusual.
That was in April. On August 16th,
I go into the office and my boss runs
into my office and he says, "Did you see
the manifesto?" And I said, "There was
no manifesto." He said, "No, they
dropped it today." And I said, "No, I
didn't hear anything about it. I didn't,
you know, run my radio in the car
normally." And he said, "They mention
you in the manifesto." I said, "What?
Not possible." I said, 'I am more
careful than anybody in this office with
my security. And he hands me the
manifesto and it says in Greek mealas,
we saw the big spy, but he was in an
armored car and we knew he was armed. So
we elected to carry out the
revolutionary sentence on the war
criminal Saunders. And he says, "You got
to go." I said, "Where?" He says,
"Home." Like now. I said, "I just
dropped my kids off at school. I can't
just go." He said, "We'll get your kids.
We'll get your wife. We'll pack your
house out. You got to go to the airport
now." So, they put me in another armored
car. They took me to the airport. They
picked up my wife, picked up my kids.
They get to the airport and my wife
says, "I want a divorce. I can't do this
anymore."
And that was the last day that we, you
know, lived together as husband and
wife. But they didn't get me. They got
Steven. His wife was, man, she was
really a something special. You know,
normally the family members of people
assassinated by 17 November, they'd go
on TV and they'd be like crying and, you
know, tearing their garments and, you
know, why can't the government do
anything? And she went in into a TV st
studio as sober as we are now and she
said, "This was not just a crime against
my husband. This was a crime against all
of the Greek people. How long are you
going to allow these criminals to
terrorize you?" They didn't do this for
political reasons. They did it because
they're criminals. And two years later,
one of them was in Pereus
with a brown paper bag with a bomb in
it, walking to the headquarters of one
of Greece's big shipping magnets. He was
going to put it under his limousine and
assassinate him. And the bomb went off.
It blew off both of his hands and blew
out his right eye. And as he was
bleeding to death, a cop ran over to him
to try to, you know, stem the flow of
the blood. And the guy confessed to
everything. I'm 17 November. The other
members are my two brothers. Dimitris
Kontinas is the main assassin. Uh,
Mikalis,
his name escapes me now, was the
founder. Confessed to everything and
then he lived.
They saved his life at the hospital. And
so they were able to get every last one
of them. And they found the weapons
cache. They found everything. They found
the old typewriter where they used to
write the manifestos. Everybody, the two
main leaders
um got 1,765
years in prison, which in Greece means
20 years. But but be 17 if you behave.
But the US government has put such
pressure on the Greek government that
you know we we've we have not said this.
So John's not saying that this is our
position. We have allowed them to
believe that if these guys are ever
released from prison, they're going to
get a bullet in the brain as soon as
they walk through the door. And so
they're they're all still in prison. Is
it easier for the CIA to actually put a
bullet to the right now?
>> Not in a NATO European Union country.
It'll never happen.
>> No.
>> So, you mentioned you were heavily armed
out there. I was always under the
impression CIA agents, it had no
weapons.
>> Yeah. If you're working in, you know,
Likenstein or Germany or Japan, no,
you're not ever ever going to be armed.
But I was not just a counterterrorism
center officer. Um, I was also assigned
in some of the most dangerous volatile
places in the world. Pakistan, I was
chief of CIA ops in or counterterrorism
ops in Pakistan, Afghanistan, um, all
all through the Persian Gulf. Um,
Athens. So, we weren't just armed, we
were like heavily armed. In fact, we
were never supposed to be unarmed. And I
I mentioned before we started kind of as
a joke, but it wasn't a joke. I'm I'm an
Orthodox Christian, Greek Orthodox, and
being in Greece, you know, there's a
church every 50 feet, right? So, there's
no excuse to not go to church. And I'd
go into church on Sunday morning with my
family, and the first thing I'd say is,
"Please God, forgive me for bringing
weapons into church."
>> Plural.
>> You don't want to shoot anybody in the
church.
>> More than one was always on you.
>> Yeah. But also, John, it's kind of weird
that you would drive the only BMW in
Greece if you want to be covert. No, but
you know what we did? I raised that as
soon as it arrived. I'm like, a 540?
I've never seen a 540 before. They were
like, "Yeah, it's first one in Greece."
I said, "I can't drive this if it says
540 on it." They drove it directly back
to the dealership and with a hair dryer,
they heated the numbers and pulled them
off. So, it didn't have any numbers on
it. It just looked like any other BMW.
Oh,
>> okay.
>> Yeah. So, it blended, right? That makes
more sense. Yeah.
>> So, they at least tint the windows for
you?
>> No. No. No. Oh, so fishbowl bulletproof.
>> Bulletproof. And I mean the windows were
like this thick. A cousin of mine uh who
lived in Athens asked me if I'd give him
a ride one time. I happened to be in
Pereus and he was a tugboat captain of
all things. So uh I said, "Sure, sure.
Hop in." And he he puts the window down.
I had forgotten to put the lock on. So
he puts the window down and it goes down
halfway and it's that thick. And he puts
his fingers on it like this. And he
turns to me and he says, "What do you do
for a living?"
And I said, "Yorgo, don't don't ask me
any questions." And then he just rolled
the window back up and he sat there the
rest of the trip home.
>> You said there was two times.
>> The second one was worse. Yeah. Yeah. I
had I had a friend um in the Middle
East. He actually introduced me to my
wife and uh he called me one day. I was
at headquarters. I had just come back
from Athens and um and he said, "Hey,
I've I've got a little bit of a
predicament I I hope you can help me
with." I said, "Sure." He said, "Uh,
he said, 'We've recruited a guy who's a
double agent, but he doesn't know that
we know that he's a double agent, and
he's been instructed to meet only with a
station chief, and it's too dangerous
for me to meet with him. Can you fly out
here every month and pretend to be me
and handle this double agent?" I said,
"Sure." I wasn't doing anything else. I
was like training Middle Eastern um
intelligence services and how to do
counterterrorism operations, but it was
boring and pro- fora. So um because I
had been evacuated from Athens, all the
good jobs had already been taken. So
they stuck me in one just to sort of,
you know, fill the time until something
else opened up. So I started flying out
to the Middle East every month and I'd
meet this guy. Um, I was, let me think,
I was 36 years old. So, this guy had to
be probably 20 years older than I was.
And, um,
and in the first meeting, it was in a
hotel. Um, I shook his hand and I gave
him a big bear hug, really just to pat
him down and see if he was wearing a
wire or if he had a gun. And, um, I had
a gun on my ankle, but I didn't have one
in a fanny pack or in a shoulder
holster. So I took my jacket off which
he later told his hand his handlers he's
unarmed
and I was like perfect that he thinks
I'm coming here unarmed. So I put my
jacket on the bed and I introduced
myself. I said you wanted to see the
chief. I'm the chief and I'm going to
tell you I'm taking this very seriously.
You are the only person that I'm
handling. So I'm only doing it because
you insisted on it. We're going to do
some fun things together. But first
thing today we're going to talk about
security. So, if I get caught meeting
with you, nobody cares. I'm going to get
expelled. I'm going to go home. I'll get
an award. It's not going to make any
difference. If you get caught, you're
going to go to prison for the rest of
your life. So, I said, you're going to
do every time we meet something called a
surveillance detection route, and I'm
going to show you how to how to come up
with one. So, you start at your house
and then you go to a shop and you buy,
you know, a light bulb and then you take
some cutthroughs through a neighborhood
and you go to another shop and then you
buy a newspaper, whatever. And then you
do some crazy kind of stuff and you go
to a third shop and buy something. And
then if you're not being followed just
to make sure then you do stuff like you
go the wrong way down the oneway street
or you keep making U-turns in the street
or whatever just to make sure you're
clean, right? And then you also do that
after our meetings. Now on the way to
the meeting, your surveillance detection
route should be at least 2 hours. Make
sure that you're not being followed. And
then when we're done, it should be at
least an hour. Got it? And he said, "Got
it. I'll do it." So the next time we
met, I said, "Did you do the
surveillance detection route?" He said,
"I did." [__] We had three teams of
guys on him. He got in his car at his
house, drove straight to the hotel,
never saw the six guys in three cars
that we had on him. So I said, "Okay,
where did you stop?" He said, "Well, I
stopped at the at the coffee shop and I
had a coffee and then I went over here
and then he was all made up. He wasn't
stopping anywhere." I said, "Okay,
that's great. So, what I want you to do
is I want you to rent a post office box.
So, I'm giving you my telephone number.
If you need anything, I want you to call
and say, I'm making this part up. You
know, the rain in Spain falls mainly in
the plane. And I'm going to say
Marzy dots and dozy and little lambs eat
ivy. And that means meet me at the
Marriott coffee shop at 10:00 tomorrow
night. Okay. He says, "Got it." I said,
"All right. Now, in the event that we
lose telephone contact, I'll be able to
leave a message for you in the post
office box. So, check the post office
box once a week." He's like, "Okay."
This guy was working for a foreign
country that I can say is arguably one
of our greatest and most dangerous
enemies in the world. Okay. So what he's
doing after the meetings is he's driving
directly to that country's embassy and
he's meeting with their station chief
and then the station chief gets on the
phone and reports on an open telephone
line everything that happened in the
meeting back to their capital. So we've
got him dead to rights.
We're doing this for months and I had
something that at the time was called a
triband cell phone. Uh they don't make
them anymore but because they don't need
to. What what it was was it was a local
number in that country but it would ring
anywhere in the world. So he called me
once and I was in Washington and he
said, "Hey, I have something. Can you
meet me for dinner tonight?" And I said,
"Oh, I I can't. I have a diplomatic
event tonight, but I can meet you
tomorrow night." And then I went
straight to Dallas airport and flew
straight to the Middle East. Got there
just in the nick of time to do the
meeting and then literally I was in that
country for 3 hours and then I caught
the 12:00 midnight flight back to London
to connect to Washington. So, I'm in the
office one day in in headquarters and I
get this panicked call from a sister
agency in Maryland and they said,
"Listen, are you handling this double
agent?" And I said, "Yeah." And the
analyst said, "He was just instructed to
kill you in the next meeting." I said,
"Get the [__] out of here." I said,
"This guy's afraid of his own shadow.
He's 20 years older than I am. He's gray
and fat and slow. He's not going to kill
me in the next meeting. Well, they
released the report saying he's been
instructed to murder an FBI or CIA
officer, rather. So, the FBI calls and
they said he's he's committed crimes
against the United States. We can snatch
him. And I said, "No, no, no." I said,
"Listen, this is going to be decided at
a pay grade above mine, so I'll get back
to you guys." Well,
all the big shots huddle in this
meeting. They're like, "We got to end
the operation now." And I said, I said,
"Please hear me out. The guy really is
afraid of a shadow. He's not going to
he's not going to shoot me. How about
this for an idea?" I said, "We do the
next meeting in the Marriott. Every
Marriott in the world is exactly the
same. You walk into the room, there's
the bathroom right there. Right. So, we
get adjoining rooms. I'll prop the door
open and he'll knock. I'll tell him come
in. I grab him. You guys bust in from
the other room and we got him. And
they're like,
"Okay, but you're going to be armed,
too." I said, "Of course I'm going to be
on." So I fly back out there and
I'm getting reports. We had a gigantic
security and surveillance team. It was
like 14 guys cuz they're watching him.
They're posted in the lobby. They're
watching the bad guys and the bad guys
get in their car and they drive to the
Marriott. So this is a major production.
So I get a call. He's walking into the
into the lobby and uh I said, "Okay, I'm
ready for him." So he calls me and he
says, "I'm here." I said, "Where?" He
said, "I'm in the lobby." I said, "Okay,
come up uh uh to the the sixth floor.
I'm in room 604." And then my colleagues
call and they said, "They got a team in
here. There are seven of them there.
There were seven of us. There's seven of
the bad guys and they're all armed and
they're just standing around." Now
imagine there are only 14 people in the
lobby of the Marriott. They're all
intelligence officers and they're all
armed and preparing for a shootout in
the Marriott.
So
he comes up and he knocks on the door
and I said, "Come in."
He walks in and I just tackle him and my
colleagues and our liazison partners
bust in from the adjoining room. I'm
sitting on him on his chest and I have
him pinned down and he's on the floor
and he's looking at me and I said to
him, "Did you really think that I am so
[__] stupid that I didn't know that
you came here to kill me today? Do you
think I am such an amateur that I didn't
know you've been a double agent since
the day we met? I'm offended." I told
him and he goes, "Allah abar. Allah
abar. I said, "Oh, Allah is not going to
be able to help you now."
So, what our liaison partners did, this
wasn't really a part of the plan, but
what the liazison partners did was one
of them pulled out a syringe and just
jams it in his thigh and it turned out
to be demoral and he was out out like a
light. Well, listen. Dirty little secret
of the hotel industry. People die in
hotels all the time. And so there's a
freight elevator and you just take the
dead body down in the freight elevator.
So we called an ambulance. We put him
with a sheet like he was dead. We took
him down in the freight elevator. We put
him in the ambulance. We got in our cars
and we took off. In the meantime, the
bad guys start talking amongst
themselves like, "Where is he? He's been
up there for a long time. Haven't heard
any gunshots. Why hasn't he checked in?
He's not answering his phone.
Something's happened. What's going on?"
And then our guys just all leave. We
left the bad guys in the in the lobby.
He wakes up like 4 hours later and we
have them tied to a chair. I was invited
to a wedding that night. The crown
prince's son was getting married and I
was so honored that they liked me enough
that they invite me to the wedding. So
he's tied to the chair. He's like, "I
[__] your mother. I [__] your sister."
And our friends are just whailing on
him. This was pre- 911, so we never laid
a hand on him. So I go, "Guys, I got to
go to this wedding, so we need to start
wrapping this up." So I said to the guy,
I said, "Look,
this is your only chance. Seriously,
it's your only chance. We know who you
are. We know who you represent, and we
want to know where the weapons are." He
said, "I'll never tell you where the
weapons are." I said, "Okay, suit
yourself." There we start whailing on
him again, punching him, black eye,
bloody mouth. I go to the wedding, had a
grand old time. I go back over to the
intelligence service headquarters and I
said, "So, where do we stand?" They
said, "He won't he won't say a word. He
just won't talk."
So, I said, "The weapons could be in his
house, obviously. Why don't we just I'll
call the locks and picks team and we'll
just, you know, pick the lock and go in
the house. They said, "Can't do it. He's
got a Filipino maid. She never leaves
the house." And I said, "Okay." I said,
"All right, let's let's declare an
environmental emergency. We'll say
there's a gas leak and we have to
evacuate." He lived in a culde-sac.
We'll evacuate the whole culde-sac. They
said, "We don't have piped gas here. We
use propane." I'm like, "My god, you
guys. Do I have to think of everything?
Bring a pro a propane truck, a tanker
truck. It has this big wheel. I do the
wheel like this. Propane's gushing out.
I'm like, "Okay, now we have an
environmental disaster. Call the [__]
fire department." And then they
evacuated all of the There were six
houses in the culde-sac.
So, the locks and picks guy comes and we
pick the lock and he's got this big
safe, like a gun safe, but a nice one, a
big one. It took it took a good half
hour to get into the gun safe and and it
was empty except and this is like a like
a cartoon. It had a little piece of
paper with a handdrawn map with an X and
it's like the weapons are here at the X.
Seriously.
>> Was it drawn in crayon?
>> Yeah, it might as well have been. So, we
all get in our cars. We drive to this
>> X. There's a town out the X is outside
this town down south. It's a it's an oil
town.
Like nobody would want to live there
unless you're working in the oil fields.
So we go as far as the road will take us
and then we park and then we have the
map and we're like following in 150 m
and then you turn right, you go to the
palm tree and make a left and then
there's a big rock and you make a right
and 50 m and there it is. And what it
was was an abandoned
bunker from an earlier armed conflict.
And it was their entire weapons cache.
>> You're talking like a giant room.
>> A giant room. Like a twocar garage
filled to the roof with weapons and
grenades and mines and you name it. It
was
>> we took everything.
I ran into one of my colleagues on that
on that operation. I'm going to say 200
10 11. I said, "Whatever happened to the
guy?" And they said, "Oh, he's he's
still in prison. He's never ever getting
out of prison." And I said, "And they
never figured out what happened, did
they?" And he said, "Nope."
But I can tell you that Hezbollah does
not exist in that country anymore.
>> Sounds like Iraq.
You probably can't confirm and you
shouldn't, but just
>> they they didn't have a crown prince.
>> Oh, you're right. You're right. So,
>> I'm not playing this game back.
>> Yeah. um after September 11 because I
know you were still in the agency right
post September 11. What was the
environment pre September 11 and then
post September 11 with counterterrorism
and then what did you end up doing
after?
>> Right. There was a there was a big and
noticeable divide between people working
on al-Qaeda and everybody else.
Everybody else is just going about their
normal business like you know there's
nothing happening in the world. people
working on al-Qaeda were panicstricken.
I I tell this story a lot. I I told it
in my first book, but it's important in
this context. July the 6th, 2001, I I
remember it like it was yesterday. I
told you I was I was in this position
where I was training Middle Eastern
intelligence services in
counterterrorism operations. And so we
had this delegation of, you know, four
mid-level guys, majors and lieutenant
colonels. And uh totally normal liaison
visit. They come in the morning. We have
a day of briefings. We take them
upstairs to meet the director. They
shake his hand. They get a little photo
op. We exchange gifts. I drop them off
at the hotel and I tell them, "Rest up.
I'll be back in three hours." And I take
them to Ruth's Chris steakhouse. And
then the next day, you do it with a
different intelligence service and a
different one again the next day after
that. So that day uh July the 6th 2001
I had booked a a 30 minute briefing
with this junior like 25 yearear-old kid
on al-Qaeda.
So the time came for the briefing and
instead of this young kid in comes
Kofheer Black, the director of
counterterrorism
and a woman who was
not affectionately known as the
red-headed devil
who was portrayed in uh Zero Dark 30. So
they come in together and I was so
surprised I stood up and I said, "Oh uh"
I said, "Gentlemen, this is Kofheblack.
He's the director of the
counterterrorism center here at the CIA.
And this is the chief of operations for
the Osama bin Laden unit. I was shocked,
like speechless. And they sat down and
Kofheer looks at these guys and just
goes right into it. He says, "Something
terrible is going to happen. We don't
know where or when, but we know it'll be
an attack on an unprecedented scale." He
said, "We're picking up chatter from the
al-Qaeda training camps where where the
instructors are on the phone with their
students and they're crying and saying,
"I'll see you in paradise." We're
hearing code words for a massive attack.
The honey salesman is coming with vast
quantities of honey or there's going to
be an enormous wedding or a great
football match is coming. They're all
codes for an attack, but we don't know
where or when it's going to be. He said,
"I'm begging you. If you have any
sources inside al-Qaeda, please help
us." And they just sat there looking at
him. And I was like, "Seriously?"
So, he got up, shook their hands, we
finished the day, I uh sent them back to
the hotel, and then I went to Cover's
office to thank him.
I said, "Kofheer, wanted to thank you
for spending the time with these guys,
but I got to ask you, I don't work on
al-Qaeda. Were you saying that for their
benefit or were you serious?" And he
said, "Oh, I'm deadly serious. Something
terrible is going to happen." And then
September 11th, it's kind of a quaint
story now, but on on the morning of
September 11th, Kofer and I had a
meeting scheduled with Condi Rice. She
was the national security adviser at the
time, and it was over the stupidest
reason. The government printing office,
this obscure little government agency
that prints all the official reports,
was going to print a report that
literally nobody would ever read called
Foreign Policy of the United States,
Greece, Turkey, Cyprus,
1949 to 1967.
Nobody's ever going to read that.
But there is a
law in the United States that says that
if an official of the United States outs
the identity of a recruited asset, we h
we have to offer that asset protection,
which means American citizenship, a
house, money to get started. Well, there
were still three guys like in their 90s
that would have been outed with
publication of these declassified
documents. It just never occurred to
anybody that someone would still be
alive whom the American embassy was
meeting in the 40s. Right? So, we had
this meeting with Connie to ask her just
to pull those cables out of the out of
the book. Right? We're not asking her to
make up different names. just pull the
cables out. Nobody's going to know.
They're nobody's going to know the
difference.
So, the driver called me and said he was
ready to pick us up and he's outside the
west uh entrance. So, I walked over to
Kofheer's office to say, "The driver's
here." And his secretary had a little TV
on her on her desk. Back in those days,
you couldn't watch TV on your computer,
right? So, she had this little tiny TV.
and one of the one of the towers of the
World Trade Center was on fire. I said,
"What happened to the World Trade
Center?" And she said, "A plane flew
into it." And I always say, because I'm
a genius, I said, "You know what? That
happened once before in 1931.
A plane flew into the Empire State
Building, but it was really foggy and
pouring down rain." I said, "It's so
crystal clear today. How can you not see
that you're flying into the World Trade
Center?" And as soon as the words came
out of my mouth, the second plane hit.
And she turned to me and she said, "Did
you see that or did I imagine it?" And I
ran back to my office and I said, "Guys,
two planes just flew into both towers of
the World Trade Center. I think we're
under attack. I think this is what
Kofheer was talking about." So we all
run into what what was then called the
bullpen. the the main office back then
of the counterterrorism center was this
enormous room where there were private
offices all around the perimeter of the
room and then everybody else sat in
cubicles. Well, there were so many
cubicles that we had to name the
pathways. So, it was like Bin Laden
Boulevard, Hezbollah Highway, right? And
we named one after George Tannet and one
after a previous head of
counterterrorism. So you could say if
you're meeting somebody, I'm at the
intersection of Winston Wy Way and
Hezbollah Highway and they would know
where to find you.
So we all run up there. There were these
TVs that were mounted on from the
ceiling and each TV was on different
networks. It was like CNN, Fox, MSNBC,
BBC, uh Canal Plus, The Russians, you
know, everybody had a TV.
dead silence in the office. We're
watching the World Trade Center burn
and then somebody behind me shouts,
"Will someone please lead?" And it was
like slapping Kofheer in the face. He's
like, "Right, you go to the director's
office and tell him X. You go to
security and tell him something else.
You go to operations and you know,
whatever." And we all continued to just
stand there and watch it. And then the
Pentagon gets hit. And then somebody
says, "We should probably assume that
the next plane is meant for us." We
didn't know the White House, the
capital, us. Those are the three logical
targets. Nobody budged.
So, one of the cops came in. We The CIA
has its own police force called the uh
the SPO, the Special Protective Office,
Special Protective Officers. And so, he
came in. He says, "Everybody evacuate."
Nobody moved. He came back in 45 minutes
later and said, "If you don't evacuate,
you'll be placed under arrest." So,
everybody evacuated. But imagine, you
know, whatever
10, 15, 20,000 people all leaving the
parking lot at exactly the same time. It
took me 2 hours to get out of my parking
space. Might as well have just stayed in
the building.
>> I could have walked home. I only lived
at seven miles from the from the
headquarters. So finally I got into the
George Washington Parkway. I got about
halfway to my apartment and um and it
was gridlock. So I just abandoned my car
on the side of the highway. I walked the
last three and a half miles. And I'll
tell you it I I could see the Pentagon
burning from from my car.
And I remember saying out loud, "How
could this happen? How could we allow
this to happen?"
And my then girlfriend called me. She
was on the sixth floor of headquarters.
She later became my wife. And uh she
said, "Where are you?" I said, "I I just
abandoned my car on the GW Parkway.
Where are you?" She said, "I'm just
getting out of headquarters." I said,
"You're not going to be able to make it
past the halfway point. Just meet me at
my house or my apartment." So, she
finally met me at my apartment. We we
went to the roof and just watched the
Pentagon burn for a couple of hours. And
then I said, "We should try to give
blood or something." Well, there there
were lines to give blood that that were
blocks long. And then finally I said,
"This is ridiculous. We we should get
back to work." So we walked back to my
car. I drove over the the grassy median,
went back to headquarters, and then I
didn't leave for the next four days. We
I I just balled up my jacket and slept
under the desk, and we took a bolt
cutters and and cut the chains on the
cafeteria. We had to write the Marriott
again because they had the food uh
concession. We had to write the
Marriotta check for $10,000. We stole
all their food and we cooked it and we
put it on folding tables in the hallway
so people could just graze as they were
working. But everybody worked. And then
like everybody else in the building the
very next day I went into the deputy
director's office. I said, "You've got
to send me to Afghanistan.
I'm one of the only fluent Arabic
speakers in the office. You have to send
me." Uh, relax. Okay, relax. Relax. Take
it easy. We're not really sure what's
going on yet. All right. I went three
times over the next six weeks. You've
got to send me to Afghanistan. Finally,
I ran into a guy that I knew, an
old-timer. He was in his 70s then. Billy
Wah, legendary
special forces guy. 17 Purple Hearts,
one short of the national record. Even
his license plate, it said 17 hits, and
it was a Purple Heart license plate.
Very cool, legendary guy. So, I run into
him. We had just done an operation
together in the Middle East and we got
back like two or three days before 911.
So I ran into him and I said, "Billy,
where you been?" And he goes, "Been in
Afghanistan." I go, "You have? What are
you doing there?" He looks at me, he
goes, "I've been killing people. What do
you think I've been doing?" I said,
"That's why they haven't sent me." Cuz I
was always the good cop and they didn't
need translators. They're not
interrogating anybody. They're just
blowing their brains out. So I was like,
"Okay, okay." So I I said, "I'm going to
try one more time." I went back into the
deputy director's office and I said,
"You have to send me to Afghanistan, and
if you don't, I'm going to quit and I'm
going to go straight to Exxon with my
Arabic and make triple what I make here,
and I'm not looking back." He's like,
"All right, take it easy. Can you go to
Pakistan?" I said, "Yes. When? tomorrow?
Yes. What do you want me to do? He said,
"I want you to be chief of
counterterrorism operations." I said,
"Good." So, I I called my girlfriend. I
said, "I got to go to Pakistan
tomorrow." She said, "Okay, how long?" I
said, "I don't know, 6 months, 9 months,
a year, I don't know." She says, "Okay,
I'll meet you at your place. I'll help
you pack." And then she drove me to the
airport the next morning and I went to
Pakistan.
>> When you went to Pakistan, do you go in
under a cover or do you go in as a CIA
coming in?
>> That That's a good question.
Normally
you would be John the import export
officer from the state department.
Um I went in like oh people say on the
plane what do you do for a living? None
of your [__] business what I do for a
living. Even the guy at the airport he
says where are you headed? And I said
Islamabad. And he goes thank you for
your service. I said don't tell anybody.
So yeah, I mean listen, if if you I
actually reported this to to the office
of central cover um because it was a
problem with cover. State pe State
Department people are not allowed to fly
business class. Well, after 911, the CIA
had a literally unlimited budget. So we
were all flying business class. So the
State Department people are back in the
cattle class. The CIA guys are in the
business class. So how do you explain
that? How do you justify that?
>> To the government or to who?
>> If somebody says, "Wait a minute. The
ambassador is back there in the back,
but you're up here in the front." You
can only say, "Oh, I got a free upgrade
so many times." Well, I I had to fly to
uh I won't say where I was fly. I had to
fly to this country in Eastern Europe
for an operation. And as a matter of
practice, I never ever talk to people on
planes. Never. I'll put in earbuds or
read or whatever. And I'm sitting next
to this guy. I had a connection to
Milan. So I I get on the plane to Milan
and this big fat Italian guy. He's like,
"What do you do for a living?" I said,
"Oh, um I'm in import export." "Oh, that
sounds mysterious." I said, "No, it's
it's not." "Well, what do you and
export?" I said, "Whatever makes the
most money. It changes all the time. It
could be little widgets or, you know,
dresses or whatever." "Oh, how long have
you been doing that?" I said, "Oh, yeah,
long time. about 10 years now, 12 years.
Uh, where are you based?
And I go, listen, if you don't mind, I
have some work to do on my uh on my iPad
here. Well, that sounds mysterious. I
go, all right, look,
I smuggle women and cigarettes from
Eastern Europe. Are you happy now? He
goes, I don't think I approve. I said, I
didn't ask for your approval. How about
shut the [__] up? and he sat there like
this the rest of the flight. Never even
looked at me the rest of the flight. But
sometimes that's what you have to do
because people just won't stop. And I
didn't know is he an Italian uh
intelligence officer? Is he a KGB
officer who maybe recognized me from
some earlier thing and got the seat next
to me? I don't know. Whoever he is, I
don't want to talk to this guy.
So
flew to Pakistan and and did my thing.
>> What color password do you use?
>> Black.
>> You use a black.
>> Way to go.
>> Yeah. By pass.
>> I saved all of them as souvenirs.
>> What the [__] is a black password?
>> Diplomatic.
>> That's the one that gets you.
>> I want one of those.
>> They're pretty sweet.
>> And you literally just
>> straight through. And there's no
questions asked, right? You just leave
them alone.
>> Wait, I do have a question. Did you fly
armed?
>> No, never. Okay.
>> Never ever.
>> So, you had to pick up wherever you were
going.
>> Yes. And sometimes
you'll have to fly from country A to
country B and you send a cable in
advance and you say, I'm arriving at,
you know, 210. I need a fully loaded 9
millimeter handgun. I need a a criate
passport and I need, you know, whatever
else. And it's it's ready for you.
>> Is it like the movies? Does it go to a
random locker
>> sometimes?
>> Yeah. If it's not too crazy sensitive,
you can go into the embassy and do it.
>> Otherwise, you know, you meet in the
back of a Pizza Hut or something.
>> Did you ever wear any costumes or masks?
>> In fact, I'm proud to say I got an award
once
because
I'll back up. The day of my hire, my
very first day at the CIA, I'm in the
big auditorium called the bubble. and
you're so excited. You can't believe
that you're actually in the CIA, you
know? It's it's just it it's something
that you never forget. So, there's a
woman on my right and there's a guy on
my left and we're all the same age.
We're all brand new. It's our first day.
So, I said to the woman on my right,
"What are you going to do here?" And she
said, "Well, the only degree I have is
not really a degree. I went to the Falls
Church Virginia Academy of Beauty."
And I said, "Seriously?" She said,
"Yeah." I said, "What are you going to
do?" She said, "They're going to train
me as a master disguise maker." And I
said, "That's cool. I would have never
thought of that." The guy, Sean, next to
me, we were friends the whole time we
were at the CIA. Shake his hand. What do
you do, Sean? He said, "Craziest thing,
they recruited me." I said, "Yeah,
that's how it was with me, too." I said,
"Why'd they recruit you?" He said, "I
did a two panel cartoon in every issue
of my college newspaper." And I said,
"So what do they want you to do here?"
He said, "They're going to train me to
be a master forger."
>> Wow.
>> And he was he became like legendary. So
12 years later,
this woman flies out to Pakistan and I'm
like, "Hey, what are you doing here?"
And she says, "I'm here for you." She
said they decided that because of the
position you're in, they wanted to
experiment with a bald-headed mask with
a combo. She was there for six weeks to
get the color of the bald head exactly
the same as my skin tone.
>> That's a long time.
>> Six weeks. And then she put those hairs
in one hair at a time. She was there
like into the night every night. And
every day I'd go look at the at the the
we call it a mask. It's not really a
mask. And the only seam it had was right
here. I didn't wear glasses yet at the
time. And so we got glasses with just
clear glass. So it covered up the seam,
but it looked like a guy with a bad coma
on. In fact, the station chief when he
saw it, he's like, "Oh my god." He said,
"It's it's fantastic." And I go, "Right.
I don't even recognize myself. He goes,
"Let's go to the ambassador's office."
So, we go into the ambassador's office
and the chief says, "Uh, ambassador, I
just wanted to introduce you to one of
our uh one of our experts. He came out
here." She goes, "In these conditions,
like we're we're at war. You have a guy
flying out." So, I go like this and I
pulled it off and I looked at her and
she's like, "Oh my god." I said, "It's
great, right?"
She's like, "Honest to god, I would
never have known it was you."
>> Did you get to keep it?
>> No.
>> What about your voice? Do they have
something to change your voice?
>> No. That you have to just kind of wing.
>> What about earplugs? Do they have like
special ear plugs where it works like
you see in the movies?
>> Like a two-way radio.
>> Not not by the time I left. I would say
probably at this point, but not not when
I left.
>> Fast forward a few years forward. when
you were with uh John K's office,
>> you went to Afghanistan to the poppy
fields,
>> right?
>> And what was
>> right, you know, after I blew the
whistle on the torture program, as you
might expect, it was a little bit tough
to find a a well-paying job. And then
one day in early 2009, January of 2009,
John Kerry called me and he said, "I'm
going to become the new chairman of the
Senate Foreign Relations Committee. I'm
going to reconstitute the investigations
office, which had been done away with in
1972.
And he said, I want you to come on as
the senior investigator. So I went up to
his office. We sat and talked for an
hour. And I said, I'll take it. So he
told me disingenuously
that I had cart blanch to do anything I
wanted, to investigate anything I
wanted. It was exactly the opposite.
That was true. But what did I know? This
this is an important guy. He was the
Democratic nominee for president. He's
the chairman of the Foreign Relations
Committee, one of the most recognized
faces in the world. And he's telling me
I can do anything I want. So I said,
"Okay, I'm going to go to Afghanistan
and I'm going to investigate the
production of heroin Poppy." So I
planned it all out. I flew to Baghdad.
I'm sorry. I flew to to uh Kabell, took
a helicopter then to Bram Air Base. This
was the only time in my career that I
ever pulled rank on someone. It's just
not my nature to to be, you know, that
guy. But um I got to Bram, they were not
at all happy to see me. And I said, I
need to fly to Kandahar and then to
Lashkar, which is the capital of Helman
Province. Helman Province is like the
center of the world for the production
of heroin. And they're like, "Nah, it's
too dangerous. we can't do it. And I
said, "No, I'm I'm doing it. We're doing
it. Let's go." No, you know, we risk,
you know, they have missiles. They're
going to shoot the helicopter. I said,
"No, listen. I outrank you and I'm
telling you, you're going to fly me to
Kandahar and Lashkar." So, we got into a
helicopter and they were dicks about it,
too. Like, they did this this spiral
landing, which you do when people are
trying to shoot Stinger missiles at you.
There were no Stinger missiles down
there,
>> so they were trying to make me throw up
is what it was,
>> but I have a strong stomach, so I'm
like, you know, whatever. We land the
helicopter and uh I met with a bunch of
um a bunch of both Afghans and Americans
in Kandahar, and then we flew to
Lashkar. So in Lashkar, there was
something called a PRT, uh provisional
re reconstruction
something. It's a state department
thing. So, you get a bunch of State
Department and USA ID people and they're
going to dig water wells and they're
going to build an electrical facility
and whatever.
So,
I I was friends with the State
Department representative there and he
knew why I was coming. So, he set up um
a translator and a security team from
the base and I said, "Let's just drive
into the poppy fields and see who we can
find." So, we drive out into the poppy
fields, and I mean, as far as you can
see, literally, it's nothing but heroin
poppy. It's all you can see. As recently
as the late 1970s, Afghanistan was a net
food exporter. It used to actually have
too much food and it would sell it to uh
Pakistan. Well, now it's just all heroin
poppy and kids have no shoes and people
are starving to death. But my god, they
have all the heroin poppy you could
possibly want. So we go go out into the
fields and sure enough, there's a farmer
out there. So we stopped and I said,
"I'm I'm from the Congress and I wanted
to talk to him about his poppy crop."
And he's like, "Okay."
So again, I have a translator, so
communication wasn't a problem. And I
said very naively, I said, "Why do you
grow poppy when instead you could grow
crops with two growing seasons like
tomatoes or onions or pomegranates?" And
he goes like this. "The Americans told
me in 2001 that if I told them where the
Arabs were, I could grow all the poppy I
wanted." I said, "What Americans told
you you could grow poppy?"
And the security guy grabs me and he
says, "Meeting over." And physically
pulls me back to the jeep.
We go back to the PRT and I get back in
the helicopter. We fly back to Bram. So
from Bram I went to Kbble. Cobble back
to Washington.
So I get there. I get to Washington and
I I said to Carrie, "You're not going to
believe what I found." And I I told him
the whole story. He's like, "Wow, that's
that's pretty powerful. You're going to
get some push back." I said, "Oh, I
know. I know who's going to push back."
So, I wrote the paper and I sent it to a
buddy of mine at DEA. He was at this at
this DEA like secret DEA facility out in
the sticks in Virginia. And he reads it
and he calls me and he says, "Buddy, you
know you're never going to get this
published, right?" And I said, "Why?"
and he said, "Afghanistan produces 93%
of the world's heroin.
Almost all of it goes to Russia and
Iran. And we want them to be addicted to
heroin. It weakens their societies. It
weakens their cultures." It's exactly
what the Chinese are doing to us with
fentinel today. But he said, "They're
never going to let you blow the whistle
on on Poppy." And sure enough, Carrie
comes to my office that after it was all
said and done, he's like, "Uh, listen, I
think it's not a good idea to publish
this this paper." And I thought, "Man,
they got to you easy." And it wasn't
just with Poppy.
There was another thing. I got a call
one day from a human rights activist,
pretty well known in Washington, human,
serious human right, not one of these
people that screams on the street
corner, like a serious intellectual.
And he says,"I need to see you. It's got
to be secret." And I said, ' Okay. I
said, 'Where do you want to meet?' He
said, "Uh, there's an empty classroom.
It's like room 204 at John's Hopkins.
I'll meet you there in an hour." I said,
"Okay." So, I go over there, go into
John's Hopkins, find the classroom, and
he says, "Listen,
have you ever heard of the Dash Deilele
massacre?" And I said, "Of course." On
November 30th and December 1st of 2001
in the northern Afghan city of Dash
delei, the entire Taliban contingent
gave up. 2,000 people gave up to the
Northern Alliance. So the Northern
Alliance calls us and says 2,000 Taliban
gave up. What what do we do with them?
And we said, "Let's truck them out into
the desert and we'll just hold them
there until we can divide them up into
smaller groups and put them in jails all
around Afghanistan." Because there there
wasn't a prison in the country big
enough to hold 2,000 people.
So the Northern Alliance boxed them up.
We called it the box up, the dashley box
up. They put them in these containers on
trucks
with no air holes, no food, and no
water.
2,000 men.
One of the 14 who lived said that when
they opened the trucks, the bodies fell
out like sardines from a can.
Well,
General Abdul Rasheed Dostam, who was
anti-Taliban,
then pro Taliban, then anti-Taliban
again, then pro Taliban again. He's the
one who ordered them into these trucks.
And we were certain that he did it
specifically to murder them. He knew
that they couldn't breathe in those
trucks. He knew that there was no water
in those trucks. So,
the reason he was telling me this is he
said that he had a witness who was 12
years old at the time and was hiding
behind a rock when the bodies started
falling out of the truck. And there were
two men there wearing blue jeans and
black t-shirts and speaking English.
So he says to me, "Who's going to be
wearing blue jeans and black shirts and
speaking English in Dash Deilele,
Afghanistan on December the 1st, 2001?"
I said, "Well, obviously." I said, "I'll
write them a letter and ask for
clarification." And the only reason I
felt somewhat bold on this issue was
that it actually came up in the 2008
campaign and Barack Obama said that if
elected, he would get to the bottom of
the Dash Deilele massacre.
So I fly back out to Afghanistan. I go
to Dash Deilele. You go to the site of
of the of the the massacre and there are
like human bones just all over the
ground.
Clothing that's tattered cuz by then it
was, you know, eight years old. So, I
wrote a letter
that Carrie signed to the CIA and I
said, "We want clarification on what
happened in Dashy Ley on November the
30th and December the 1st, 2001." And I
had these like 10 questions and I sent
it signed John Kerry, chairman.
Six weeks pass and a colleague of mine
comes into my office and he goes, "Hey,
you got a response from the agency to
your letter uh on d'achle." I said, "I
just checked my mail an hour ago. I
didn't see any response." He said, "They
classified it top secret." Well, I only
had a secret clearance at the time. So,
I said, "What did it say?" He says, "It
said, "Go [__] yourself."
I said, "That's how they want to play
it." So, I go to Carrie and I said,
"This is unacceptable." and he says,"I
think we should probably kill this
investigation." I said, 'Senator, come
on. Every time I I'm on to something,
you tell me to to kill it. Well, you
know, we don't want to make things hard
for the White House. That wasn't the
truth. That wasn't what he was thinking
of. He was thinking that I can't make
any waves at all because I so
desperately want to be Secretary of
State.
There were only two times that I ever
gave Carrie unsolicited advice.
He gave a speech in which he called
Bashar al-Assad my dear friend several
times. Every Lebanese in Washington
called me. The Lebanese ambassador
called me and he's like, "What the
fuck?" So I said, "Senator, you've got
to stop calling Bashar al-Assad my dear
friend." He goes, "Well, we are friends.
We we rode motorcycles together down to
the Golden Heights." I said, "I
understand that, but be that as it may,
he's a genocidal maniac and every
Lebanese in Washington is calling me and
they're furious with you." He's like,
"All right, all right. I'll back off."
The other time was he asked me to write
him a speech. Um, and one thing I
learned about Carrie is he thinks that
he is smarter than everybody else in the
room. And so, he never sticks to the
speech. He always goes off topic. And
it's never smart. and it's never
appropriate. So, I write this speech,
he's delivering it at the at the um
sorry, not the Smithsonian, the um
Brookings Institute and then he goes off
off speech and I was like, "Fuck." And
he says, "You know, I was supposed to be
the Secretary of State, not Hillary
Clinton." And I'm in the audience and
I'm going like this.
But Obama, you know, he's playing
politics and he had to throw a bone to
Hillary. And I'm going like this. And
after it was all done, I was like,
"Senator, it it really doesn't look
good. It sounds like sour grapes. Like
you thought you were really great and
then the president thought you weren't
really as great as you thought you were
and gave it to somebody else." Well,
that's that's not how it was. I said, "I
know that's not how it was, but that's
how it sounds. You got to stop telling
people in public that you were supposed
to be the Secretary of State." And so he
backed off. But anyway, um he told me to
kill the investigation, which I did. And
then finally in 2010, the Democrats lost
I think it was four Senate seats and we
had our budget slashed. And my boss
said, my immediate boss, the staff
director, he said, 'You know, the budget
is going to be tough for us. I said, I
know, I know. I said, 'Don't throw me
out into the street. Let me line
something up first and then I'll just
resign. So, that's what I ended up
doing. Um, but it was clear to me that
Carrie was absolutely not going to do
anything at all to embarrass Barack
Obama. Nothing. And then as a postcript
after I got arrested,
I wrote him an email to his uh to his
personal email account and I said, "You
got to help me out here. You know that
this is wrong." I said, "I have five
kids." I said, "Can you please just talk
to the president and ask him to commute
my sentence? The the the conviction
would stand. DOJ saves face, but I would
get to work and provide for my family."
Two days later, he wrote back and all he
said was, "Please do not ever attempt to
contact me again."
And it was because he wanted to be
Secretary of State.
That's all he lived for.
>> Seems like in politics it's just about
like everyone for themselves.
>> Oh my god. And everything is
I should say nothing is as it appears.
The day that he called me to interview
me for that job, it was in his Senate
office.
and his office was in the uh in the
Russell Senate office building which is
the original the the big historic you
know neocclassical beautiful gorgeous
historic building. Interestingly enough
his office was immediately next door to
John McCain's which was kind of
important. So I go into the office I had
never met him before. I go into the
office and the first thing you notice,
you know, these are 20 foot ceilings,
gigantic. Literally from the floor to
the ceiling are framed pictures of
Carrie with every leader in the world
from Gorbachev to the Daly Lama to
Netanyahu to the Queen Elizabeth,
everybody. It's very impressive. It's
like an altar to yourself, which is not
cool, but it was very impressive to me.
But more importantly, in my view, as
soon as you walk in, there's a little
credenza right here that most people
would just walk right past, not paying
attention to it. But there were three
things on the credenza that really stuck
with me. The first was a framed picture
of Carrie with John Lennon. Very cool.
And they're like, you know, giving each
other noogies. Very cool. Who wouldn't
want a picture like that, right? On the
other side was a picture of Carrie with
Peter, Paul, and Mary, the folk group.
And he was close to all of them. He Mary
Travers died while I was on staff and um
and Carrie gave the eulogy at her
funeral. Very touching. But in the
middle was a shadow box and in the
shadow box it had his silver star, his
three bronze stars and his purple heart.
But there's a famous story about Carrie.
It's the story that made him famous.
when he came back from Vietnam to
protest the Vietnam War, he threw those
medals over the White House fence
and then he testified before the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee later that
afternoon and famously said, "Who wants
to be the last man to die for a lie?"
But there are the medals right there. So
after the meeting was over, the staff
director said, "So how did it go?" Staff
director was an awesome guy. I liked him
a He was a member of the Kennedy family,
which struck me as kind of funny. But I
said, "It went great." He offered me the
job and I told him I'd take it. But I
said, "Tell me that the shadow box with
the medals." I said, "What's up with
that?" Like, "Everybody in America knows
he threw his medals over the White House
fence." He goes, "Come on." He goes,
"Those medals were the most important
things in his life. He went to the PX
that morning and bought copies of the
medals and threw those over the White
House fence."
I said as soon as he did it, he
announced his candidacy for lieutenant
governor of, you know, Massachusetts and
then became a star, was in Congress two
years later in the Senate right after
that. He's like, that was all all a big
lie.
>> So, what you see on TV with the
politicians,
>> they're all dogs, every last one, except
John Kerry, and I'm telling you this as
as a progressive who is to the left of
the Democratic party. John McCain was
one of the most one of the most
wonderful, kind, selfless patriots I've
ever encountered in my life. You don't
have to dis you don't have to agree with
him, I should say, on the issues to
respect him for the person he was. You
know, the reason why I said it was
important that his office was next door
to Carrie's is every time Carrie and I
would come out of the office and McCain
would come out, he would go out of his
way to come up and shake my hand and
say, "How are you doing, John?" And I'd
say, "I'm doing great, Senator. How are
you doing?" And then finally Carrie
says, "Why don't you and McCain get a
room or something?" And I said, "No,
it's it's because he was tortured and I
put my whole career on the line to call
out torture." I said, "He's really he's
really a good guy." And then the week
that I got out of prison, I got a call
from his um chief of staff and he said,
"Senator McCain says, "Welcome home."
And he wants to know what he can do to
be helpful. And I said, "He can get me
my pension back." I said, "Obama took my
pension." So what we ended up doing is
my attorney worked with McCain staff to
to write an amendment to the National
Defense Authorization Act. And all the
amendment said was all Americans
who have been convicted of violating the
Intelligence Identities Protection Act
of 1981
between October 1st and October 31st of
2012 shall hereby have their pensions
reinstated. Well, of course, I'm the
only person in the world that that
describes, but before we could get it
in, he got brain cancer and then he died
and so we could never get it into the
NDAA.
But he was a good man. He was the only
He was the only guy on Capitol Hill who
really went to the mat for me. My
congressman from Virginia, uh, Jim
Moran, he he was a great guy, too. And
he put his reputation on the line for
me. And then there were a couple other
like Lloyd Dogget, a Democrat from Texas
who got up on the floor of the House and
said, you know, release John Kuryaku.
But McCain really put his money where
his mouth was.
>> So, I've got some questions that I've
asked our audience to prepare for you.
>> Are you ready for some
>> questions from the audience?
>> All right. So, the first one is, what's
one truth about the CIA that you wish
every American understood, but most will
not? I have a reputation as being
something of a CIA dissident.
Um, I don't see myself as a dissident.
So, I'm going to say one truth is the
CIA is made up of tens of thousands of
brilliant, patriotic people who want to
do nothing more than to protect the
country. Okay, that's truth number one.
Truth number two is
it is also made up of thousands of
people who will break every law,
lie to the congressional overseers,
overthrow governments, murder innocents
knowing that they could get away with
it. And so on the one hand, you've got
people who really, really want to do the
right thing. And on the other hand, you
have a band of bloodthirsty murderers
who need to be brought under control.
What's the most dangerous lie the US
government is still telling the public?
>> In my very first week on the job, it was
a week of briefings, right? Got to meet
the director, the deputy directors, the
head of personnel, the head of security,
the head of this, the head of that. the
head of security came to talk about um
counter intelligence and he said for
example there's a steakhouse right down
the road from uh from the agency. He's
like don't ever eat there. The KGB
thinks we all eat there. So 7 days a
week the place is just jammed to the
gills with KGB agents.
So we don't eat there. Go another couple
of miles. There are plenty of
restaurants farther down the road.
Well, it's not just the KGB that we have
to worry about or the Chinese or the the
Cubans or whatever. He said
the Israeli embassy has two declared
intelligence officers. Declared meaning
they're known, they're officially known
to the CIA, one from Assad, one from
Shinbet. The FBI, again, this is 35
years ago, the FBI has been able to
identify, he said,
187 undeclared Mossad agents spread all
around the United States to steal
secrets from our defense contractors.
Now, we give the Israelis 99%
of the technology that we have. They're
trying to steal that last hund, that
last 1%. I'll give you an example. the
F-35, right? We went to the Israelis. We
said, "Look, we're developing this new
fighter called the F-35. It's going to
be the best fighter." They said, "We
want it. We want the first ones." We
said, "Great. We'll give them to you.
We're going to call yours the F-35I. I I
for Israel, and what we're going to do
is we're going to very slightly degrade
the avionics. So, God forbid if one of
them gets shot down, the Iranians or the
Russians or the Chinese can't, you know,
get the avionics." They said, "No, we
want the F-35." We said, "No, we're not
going to give it to you." In the
meantime, at around the same time, the
United Arab Emirates came to us and
said, "Hey, we heard about this F-35. We
want the F-35." We said, "Great, we'll
give it to you. We're going to call it
the F-35E for Emirates. We're going to
slightly degrade the avionics, so God
forbid if it gets shot down." The
Iranians don't get it. They said, "Fine,
we'll take it."
Well, the Israelis
are in Northrup Grumman and Loheed
Martin and Boeing and every other
defense contractor in America trying to
steal every one of our defense secrets
to upgrade the avionics to have at least
what we have and more. The Israelis are
not our friends, period. A a story that
I tell frequently uh in podcasts is my
very first liaison briefing. I was brand
new analyst. I had been around for just
a few months and my boss said, "Hey,
you're going to brief the Israelis with
a whole team of Iraq analysts. I was the
most junior, so I went last." So we we
normally do liazison briefings in a
conference room at headquarters, not the
Israelis. They are not permitted in CIA
headquarters because every time they
would come, they would give us gifts.
And the gifts always had listening
devices embedded in them with batteries.
And we're like, "You guys have to stop
doing this." They're like, "Oh, we
brought you a seal of the CIA. You
should hang it in the director's
office." And it's all full of listening
devices. So, we're like, "You guys can't
come here anymore." So, we had to rent a
safe house. And we meet with the
Israelis in this safe house. So, you
know this story. We go around the we go
around the table and it's the Mossad guy
and or MSAD woman it was at the time and
Shinbet guy and because I was an overt
employee at the time I used my real name
which I was supposed to do. We all did.
None of us were undercover. So that
would go around the table political uh
briefing, economic briefing, military
briefing, oil briefing, you know this
one, that one it came to me. I was uh
the Iraq leadership analyst. So I said,
"My name is John Kuryaku and I'm going
to brief you on Saddam Hussein's uh
psychological state." And the guy looks
at me over his glasses and he goes, "You
are
Jewish." And I said, "I am not
recruitable. Don't even think about it."
We got back, I was furious. We got back
to the office and everybody was
laughing. They were like, "They do that
to every one of us. They're so crude and
so heavy-handed.
And my boss said, "Did they pitch you?"
And I said, "Yeah, right to my face in
front of everybody. Now I got to go to
security and write a report." Which I
did. But this is what they do. They're
happy to recruit as many Americans in
positions of authority as they possibly
can because they don't really give a
[__] about the the relationship. They
know that politically
they have they have us by the balls. And
so we're not going to change our foreign
policy toward Israel. No matter what
they do to us, we're never going to
change. I mean, just look at what's
happening today. If you are not 1,000%
pro-Israel, and not even really
pro-Israel, that's really kind of a
misnomer. Pro- Netanyahu,
then you will be primar
in most cases you will lose. and they'll
find somebody who's pro- Netanyahu to
replace you in Congress. It's
unacceptable.
>> How do we change it?
>> Ah, see, that's really the hard
question.
There's really no easy way to change it.
I'll tell you there there is actually,
but it'll never happen. You force Apac
to register as a foreign agent just like
everybody else does. Like every single
lobbying firm or lobbyist in Washington
who has anything even vaguely to do with
a foreign country has to register under
FAR, the the Foreign Agents Registration
Act except Apac.
>> What would that change?
>> Well, then they would have to report
everything that they're doing in
government and risk a felony conviction
if they fail to report. Plus, if you are
a foreign representative or a foreign
entity, you cannot donate to an American
political campaign. And right now, I
mean, the Israelis own Capitol Hill
because they they donate millions and
millions of dollars to uh to friendly
candidates through Apac. Remember, Apac
is called the American Israel political
a public affairs committee. public
affairs, not political action, not
lobbying.
It's public affairs. They're like,
"Well, we're just we're just trying to
educate people on what Israel is like."
Like, "Oh, that's you're going to stick
with that story area." Okay. We hear
torture. We hear enhanced
interrogations. We have no idea what
that means, right?
>> I could just imagine what is it like
pulling the fingernails that you see on
TV. What is the torture? What is the
enhanced interrogation?
>> In most cases, it's not so crude. So,
there are enhanced interrogation
techniques and then there's all the
other [__] that they did that they
didn't have approval for that they just
figured we're going to do it and
nobody's going to do anything about it.
So, enhanced interrogation techniques as
they were approved by the Justice
Department were mostly not something
that I would call torture. Like if I
grab you by the shirt and I say, "Damn
you, answer my questions." That's not
torture. If uh the the next the next
most serious one was called the belly
slap, right? It makes a cracking sound,
makes a handprint, a little bit
humiliating. That's not torture.
>> But are you like naked, chained up?
>> Not yet. That comes
>> keyword. Yeah.
>> Yeah. A smack across the face. That's
not very nice, but it's probably not
torture. But then you get into things
like strip the guy naked, chain him to
an eyebolt in the ceiling and make it so
he can't kneel or sit or lay or get
comfortable in any way. Chill the cell
to 50° Fahrenheit and then throw a
bucket of ice water on him every hour.
We murdered uh prisoners with that
technique. It's called the cold cell.
Sleep deprivation is another one. Uh Don
Rumsfeld was the secretary of defense at
the time. He famously said that he
didn't believe that there was such a
thing called sleep deprivation because
he said, "Look at me. I have a standup
desk in my office. I don't even have a a
chair and I'll stand there and work for
24 hours, sometimes longer than 24
hours." That's not what we were talking
about. What we're talking about is being
stripped naked and chained to that
eyebolt so you can't get comfortable
knowing that the American Psychological
Association has done studies showing
that people begin to lose their minds at
day seven with no sleep. They begin to
die from organ failure at day nine. But
the CIA was was authorized to keep
patients patients to keep prisoners
awake for up to 12 days. Well, we
murdered prisoners doing that. The
Justice Department never said we could
murder people. They said we could use
these techniques which are not torture.
They're enhanced
parts of the interrogation. Well, that
was just silly. But then there were
other things, especially with Abu
Zubveda. things that we did to Abu Ba
that were never authorized by anybody.
We learned during an interrogation that
Abu Zuba had an irrational fear of bugs.
And so we put him in a coffin with a
diaper. We poured a box of cockroaches
on him and then closed the coffin and
just listened to him scream.
We would open the coffin long enough
every few days to give him water and
food and change his diaper and then seal
it back up again.
>> The [__] is that?
>> Why wouldn't he just talk?
>> He was talking. He was talking.
>> These people would talk and still be to
>> Yes, that was the issue.
And listen, I told Abu Beta right after
we caught him. I said, "I am the nicest
guy that you're going to meet in this
experience." I said, "My colleagues,
they're not nice like I am. So, if you
only do one thing, it's that you have to
cooperate. You have to answer their
questions." And he said, "You seem like
a nice man, but you're the enemy, and
I'll never cooperate."
I said, "Well, suit yourself." Then,
when the CIA plane came in to take him,
he was petrified, crying. Three FBI
agents and I carried his gurnie out to
the plane. I was I was carrying the
gurnie with one hand and holding his
hand with the other. He was balling and
we we put him on the plane. We tied him
down on the luggage rack at the back of
the plane and I leaned over and I said,
"Remember, you have to cooperate." And
he smiled at me and I said, "Good luck."
And then took off. Well, then
he he ends up a week later at the secret
site and um he was very very severely
wounded during the capture and so they
allowed him six weeks to just get his
wounds to heal. Well, there was an FBI
agent by the name of Ali Sufan,
ethnically Egyptian, American FBI agent,
fluent in Arabic. Ali began to
interrogate him. Now, listen, I hate the
FBI. I do.
But there are no better interrogators in
America than the FBI. They've been doing
it since the Nuremberg trials in 1945
and 1946. They know exactly what they're
doing. And the way they succeed is they
establish a rapport with a prisoner,
right? You don't rape him or beat him or
starve him or electrocute him. You sit
across the table from him. And sure,
he's got handcuffs on. He's chained to
the table, but you offer him a cup of
coffee or an orange or a cigarette or if
he's really helping you out, a piece of
paper and a pencil to write to his
parents. And eventually, sometimes it
takes days, weeks, months, who knows?
Eventually, he's going to open up. And
Abu Zuba really opened up and gave us
actionable intelligence that saved
American lives.
But the CIA and especially the two CIA
contractors, the two psychologists who
came up with the program, they wanted to
see how it worked. And so George
Tennant, the CIA director, went to
President Bush on July the 31st of 2002
and said, "Please turn the prisoner over
to us." And Bush, because he didn't know
what the frag was going on in in the
world, did that. And so Ali Sufan was
pulled back. In fact, Robert Mueller was
the FBI director at the time. He knew
exactly what the CIA was going to start
doing. And so, not only did he pull his
people out, he pulled all FBI personnel
out of the country that the secret
prison was in. He didn't even want his
people to be in the same country while
the CIA was torturing its prisoners. And
so, they immediately began torturing
Obeda on August the 2nd, 2002. and he
went silent. So they tortured him for
about six weeks and then the FBI came
back. He was furious and it took Ali
more than a month to get him talking
again. And he's like, "Why did you guys
do that to me? I was telling you
everything you wanted to know." And he
said, "That that wasn't that wasn't us.
That was these other guys from a
different organization."
Ali continued to interrogate him for
another couple of months and then the
contractors came back uh James Mitchell
and Bruce Jessen, the two the two
contract psychologists and just started
torturing him even more mercilessly.
They waterboarded him 83 times. They
actually killed him at one point. His
heart stopped beating and they had to
revive him with CPR so they could
torture him more.
And then after that, he never told us
anything.
>> Do you think I know the FBI, the CIA had
MK Ultra with the mind control
techniques. Do you think they're doing
anything similar to that or are they
that?
>> That's a very good question, and it's
impossible to come up with a definitive
answer, but let me give you some
background first. MK Ultra was a program
that started in the early 1950s, and it
started by accident. We had a source who
turned out to be a fabricator saying,
"The Russians are doing mind control
experiments." And we were like, "Oh my
god, we're going to be behind the
Russians. All right, we got to do our
own mind control experiments.
The Russians are doing ESP experiments."
We said, "Oh my god, we have to hire all
this the psychics in America and try and
get them to do mind control."
So we came up with this thing that was
called MK Ultra
and it was composed of several different
sub operations
MK chipwit for example. So we were doing
things like what would happen if we gave
people LSD and they didn't know it.
Let's try that. See what happens. Well
who should we do it to? Let's do it to
our own people. Just see what happens.
Well I'll tell you what happens. They
start jumping out of windows and off of
roofs of buildings and committing
suicide. They're like, "That didn't
work." Okay,
why don't we hire prostitutes?
This is true. We'll hire prostitutes in
San Francisco. We'll have them pick up
John's. We'll bring the John's back to a
safe house that we control. We'll dose
them with LSD.
will tie them up and interrogate them
and see if they'll tell us their deepest
secrets. No, they just went nuts. That's
all that happened. And then we release
them and then they're just wandering the
streets of San Francisco nuts.
Then they said, "How about if we come up
with a germ and we spread the germ all
around San Francisco
and see if people get sick?" So they
came up with this germ. They waited
until a really foggy day when the air is
very heavy and it sits on the ground,
right? Because what's fog? It's a cloud
that sits on the ground. And
within days, 11 people went to hospital
emergency rooms with this rare strain of
upper respiratory infection. We're like,
"Hey, now we can do that in Havana,
in Moscow, in East Berlin."
But none of this led to, you know,
reading minds or manurion candidates or
none of it worked. But it was brutal.
And we made people insane. We made
people commit suicide. We split
families.
And this was monstrous. Well, it it
became public in 1975 in in the Church
and Pike Committee hearings on Capitol
Hill. So, it lasted from 1952 to 1975.
and and chairman uh Church, senior
senator from Idaho, specifically ordered
the CIA director not to destroy the
documents related to MK Ultra. He
immediately went back to headquarters
and destroyed 80% of the documents. So,
we only have a little historical
understanding of what happened with MK
Ultra. Everything else was was shredded.
People ask me all the time, is there MK
Ultra today? Honestly, I have no idea.
It's not called MK Ultra, but it's
impossible to know what the CIA is doing
on these mind control issues. Now,
they're doing other things
technologically that we know thanks to
Wikileaks and Josh Schulty and the uh
Vault 7 revelations. We know that they
can take remote control of your car and
make you drive off a bridge.
>> Any car.
>> Any car. any car that has a computer in
it, which is every car, unless you're
driving a, you know, 57 Chevy or
something.
>> Uh, we know that they can take any smart
TV, any smart TV, and turn the speaker
into a microphone so that it broadcasts
what's being said in the room even while
the TV is off. Another thing that they
did was they infected computers
domestically which is illegal but then
in the code they embedded lines of code
written in either Farsy or Cerrillic.
>> That's marble right project marble.
>> Correct.
>> So they could point say it wasn't us it
was the Russians Iranians they did it.
Look the code. They forgot to translate
these lines of code. They're still in
Russian and Farsy. No it was it was us.
So, we don't really know what they are
doing. And I and I'll I'll say this. I'm
going to caveat this by saying I've been
out of the CIA for 21 years now.
That is a lifetime technologically
speaking. It's a different world today
than it was when I left the CIA. God
knows what they can do that we haven't
found out yet. It's impossible to say.
What traits are they looking for? They
are looking for people who have
sociopathic tendencies,
not sociopaths. Right? Sociopaths have
no conscience. They're unable to feel
guilt. You don't want a sociopath
because sometimes they can't stop
themselves and they will feel utterly
remorseless after having killed
somebody. And as a result, they blow
through the polygraph because they don't
have a conscience. People who have
sociopathic tendencies do have a
conscience but are also willing to work
in these legal and moral and ethical
gray areas. And I'll give you an
example. In the um in the interview
process, I was with like two other guys
and a woman and the instructor is giving
us this oral exam and he said, "Let's
say you are a case officer overseas and
you get a cable from headquarters
telling you that they need the latest
economic data from Indonesia. You then
go to meet the Indonesian economic
officer and you take him to lunch and
you have a great time and you take him
to dinner. You have another great time.
You introduce the wives. They hit it
off. You spend time, you know, go on
vacation for the weekend. Your kids are
playing together. Everything's going
perfectly.
But you do this for six months and then
you realize this guy's really not
recruitable. There's really nothing that
he needs from you and there's no
weakness that he has. He's not a drunk.
He's not a gambler. He's not a an
[__] who, you know, has fallen a foul
of his boss. He's just a guy,
but headquarters really needs the data.
So, what do you do? And the guy raises
his hand. He says, "You double down and
you do it for another six months. Spend
more money on the guy." And um and the
woman says, "Maybe you get the wives
more involved. get the wives to get
closer and then you can work it through
the wife. And I'm listening to all this
like what? So I raise my hand. I go,
"You break into the Indonesian embassy
and you steal it." He goes, "That's
exactly what you do. You break into the
Indonesian embassy and you steal it.
Don't waste another six months on this
guy. He's not going to give you
anything." That's a sociopathic
tendency. A normal person wouldn't
voluntarily say, "I'm going to break
into the Indonesian embassy and steal
their documents."
I would, maybe you wouldn't, but that's
what a sociopathic tendency is.
>> What other questions do they ask you?
Like qualifying questions.
>> Describe your relationship with your
mother. Like, what's the right answer
there? I said, yeah. I said, my my mom
and I are close. She was nurturing and
kind and supportive. And was your father
the disciplinarian in the family? And I
said, "No, actually, my dad's a big,
strong guy, and I think he was always
probably afraid that he would scare us
or hurt us or something." So, no, he was
never. He was always kind of a
sweetheart.
"Have you ever betrayed a friendship?"
And I said, "Ooh, I don't think so. Let
me think about it for a minute." They
go, "No, no." That's the response we
were looking for. I said, "Okay." They
said, 'We need for you to go in the next
room and give us some hair, some blood,
and some piss. I said, ' Okay.' So,
there's a nurse in there. She plucked
out my hairs and took my blood and I
pissed in a cup. And I went home. My
wife goes, "How'd it go?" I said, "I
have no idea. I have no idea if I gave
the right answers or crazy wrong
answers. I have no idea what they were
looking for."
And then they hired me
>> because I guess they were the right
answers. Did you take any tests like
written tests?
>> Thoughts?
>> I aced those, man. That that was the
first thing you do. So, they gave me
they gave me three written tests. Um,
one was current events. It was like
laughingly easy.
>> Was it multiple choice?
>> Multiple choice. A, B, C, and D. Fill in
the little oval.
Embarrassing. Like any anybody who you
don't even have to read the watch to
post. If you just glance at the headline
as you're walking past the newspaper
box, you're going to you're going to be
fine.
Then the second one was um it was a map
of the world. You had to unfold this big
map of the world and none of the
countries were labeled and you had to
write in the names of all the countries.
I was always a nut for maps when I was a
kid. So that was easy. That was like a
little trepidacious about West Africa,
but it was easy otherwise. And then the
third one was tough. It was thousands of
questions and you have to say agree or
disagree, right? So, it's like I wish I
could conduct a symphony orchestra.
I don't care one way or the other. Let
me just fill one in. I like boxing.
And I remember this one specifically
because I really have never had a
position on boxing, but you have to say
one or the other. Agree, disagree. And I
thought, I like this this new guy,
Tyson, right? If if he's fighting, yes,
I'll watch it. And my mom went to school
with Ernie Shavers. He was the
heavyweight champion of the world. So
whenever we'd go to visit my
grandmother, we'd stop by Ernie Shaver's
house and say hello.
So I I think I put agree. I think. But
then like 645 questions later, it says I
like boxing. And I thought, dang, what
did I say the first time? I can't
remember. I think I said yes. And then a
thousand questions later, I like boxing.
I'm like, god darn it. So really,
they're just looking for patterns. They
wanted to see if you were trying to fake
your way through to trick them. How long
did this test take?
>> It was scheduled from 8 in the morning
to noon for the three and I finished by
like 10. I was the first one. There were
300 people in the auditorium. It was
George Washington University Medical
School Auditorium. I was the first one
to get up and leave. And the proctor
says, "You're done already?" And I go,
"Yeah."
I just passed it in. My wife picked me
up. She goes, "How'd it go?" I said, "I
don't know." I said, "The first two I
blew the doors off, but the third one,"
I said, "I don't know what the heck they
were looking for."
>> Was it a MyersBrigg kind of a question?
>> MyersBriggs came later.
>> They do that, too?
>> Yeah. Oh, boy. They live and die by
MyersBriggs.
Uh, ENTJ.
>> You are ENTJ.
>> How are ISTJs?
>> Analysts.
>> Ah, analyst. That's not good.
>> There are no um um uh introvert case
officers. You're going to fail.
>> Oh, you're right. Because you have to
>> you have to loveing
>> and you have to love hanging out with
some of the most horrible and despicable
criminals on earth.
I was very proud of the way I was able
to to get people to think that I
genuinely liked them.
>> Well, you asked them questions, right?
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah. And you have to be up on
everything. Like there was this guy I
really really needed to recruit and he
was a big fan of um a big Broadway
musical fan. I don't know the first
thing about broad Broadway musicals. So,
I accidentally bumped into him and um
and I said just off-handedly, "Oh, you
know, I was just on vacation and I went
to see the producers on Broadway and I
laughed out loud." Total lie. I laughed
out loud for two hours. I had read a
review in the Washington Post about the
producers and I go, "Spring time for
Hitler and Germany." I said, "Oh my god,
I still laugh about it." Totally made it
up. I had never seen it. And he's like,
"Oh my god, it's my favorite musical. Oh
my goodness." I said, "We should go to
Broadway together sometime. I would love
to do that." Well, you know, we have
unlimited budgets. So, you want to go to
Broadway? I'll take you to any Broadway
show you want. Thousand tickets right in
the front row, and then I'll take you
out for a $1,000 dinner afterwards. And
then I got him. What was the easiest? Uh
was it reward or ego?
>> 95% studies have been done about this
internally. 95%
of sources are recruited for the money.
They do it just it's a cash transaction.
Of the remaining 5%
some just really really love the United
States. Some do it for revenge. They
hate their bosses. They got passed over
for promotion.
Um, and then some do it because they
just love the excitement. They've seen
all the Bond movies. They've seen the
Born movies. And it's they just need
excitement in their lives and the
clandestinity of it all. You know,
you're meeting at 2:00 in the morning in
the parking lot of the, you know, the
closed down yacht club and talking in
code. You know, I said earlier the guy
calls and he's like, "Hey, how are you?"
Good. How are you?
Oh, the sky was so blue today and that
means I need to see you, you know,
tomorrow at
this restaurant outside of town that we
talked about last month. And then you
say yes and but it's supposed to rain
tonight, meaning no, that place is
compromised. We need to do the fallback
place. So you you organize all these
codes in advance
um just so you don't just so you
minimize the possibility of getting in
trouble. Funny thing, one of the things
they told us if we ever got caught
meeting a meeting a source at a hotel.
This never ever happened to me, but it
did happen to a woman that I knew who
worked in Latin America. If you're in
the hotel doing a meeting, and most of
the meetings are going to be either in a
hotel or in a car, right? the more
sensitive sources you're going to meet
in the car and then just keep driving
around. But in a hotel, if they start
banging on your door, rip off your
clothes and jump into bed, both of you,
because you're going to be gay for a
minute. So when they finally break down
the door, they're like, "Oh [__] we
thought you were meeting because we
thought you were CIA and you, oh my god,
no, you're just gay."
And then everybody's okay.
You you had said if someone Oh, if
you're in a [__] hole country and
somebody two two guys come in a room,
you shoot.
>> Yeah.
>> Has that ever happened to you when
you've been in a [__] hole country?
>> Oh, I I spent most of my adult life in
[__] hole countries, but that never
happened to me. Only in training, and
I'll never forget it. We were we were at
this shooting range at one of the CIA
training facilities and the shooting
range includes
like a a mockup of a [__] hole hotel
and um we were all in a van outside.
There were like 10 of us in this van and
I volunteered to go first. So I went in.
They said, "Okay,
sit on the bed and then react." I said,
"Okay." Okay. So, I'm sitting on the bed
and somebody knocks on the door and I
said, "Just a minute." And I stood up to
answer the door and the door flies open
and they both start speaking to me in
Spanish. I don't speak Spanish. One of
them's holding a a vacuum cleaner. So, I
go, "Wait a minute. Wait a minute. I
didn't order I didn't order
housekeeping." And then he drops the
vacuum cleaner and goes bang bang bang.
And he got me with paintballs. And I go,
"Fuck."
And he says, "You should have shot us as
soon as we open the door."
And I said, "Honest to God, it's a
lesson I will never forget." And they
said, "Take your shirt off, drop it
here, and don't tell anybody else in the
van what happened." So I go back to the
van and everybody's like, "Well," and I
just said, "It's not good, but I can't
talk about it." And one by one they each
came back and all 10 of us failed. But
it was a lesson I will never forget. So
anytime
I detected trouble,
the first thing I did was I unzipped my
fanny pack just so I could grab the gun
and just start shooting
every time. I never had to shoot, but I
was ready every time
because of that exercise. Once you
shoot, you got to just leave the country
as fast as possible.
>> And they taught us if you are going to
draw the weapon, you have to kill the
guy. We're not going to wave it around
and say, "Hey, get back in your car."
You know, no. Two shots both to the kill
zone from the chest up to the neck or
the head, right? Two shots and then we
have to get you out as fast as we
possibly can. If Hollywood made a movie
about your life, which moment would be
the climax?
>> The cl the climax of horse coming just
before the deny mole. Okay. I'd say
walking out of prison in 2015. I was
utterly completely and totally
unrepentant.
I I I was out of prison for like two
days. I gave an interview to the BBC and
this guy, you know, the BBC, they always
try to bait you, right? because they
love this slugfest.
And the guy's like, "Well, you're not
you're not apologetic at all. You're not
repentant at all." And I said, "No, I'm
not at all. I would do it again tomorrow
if I had the opportunity." I was like,
"Oh, okay." I was like, "Okay,
next question then." What? You want me
to apologize? No. Let the torturers and
the murderers apologize. They're the
ones that should apologize to the
American people.
So, I left it there.
>> You also wrote a book about 20 skills
that the CIA taught you to survive in
prison.
>> Right. It was it was called um Doing
Time Like a Spy: How the CIA Taught Me
to Survive and Thrive in Prison.
>> Yeah.
>> I started off the book as a joke,
>> right? These were 20 life skills, life
rules that they taught us. Some of them
were tongue andcheek like admit nothing,
deny everything, make counter
accusations. We even had coffee cups
that said that. But I mean, it's
serious. And I actually employed that in
prison. Um, not with prisoners, but with
these morons who were the the guards,
like these mental defectives. You know,
to be a prison guard in in the United
States, you only need to have a GED or
be working on your GED and no felony
convictions. That's it. I say in the
book that one of the things that struck
me early on was that the guards have to
do mail call every day at four o'clock,
but usually they didn't. They had a
prisoner do mail call. Why? Because the
guards couldn't read.
They just simply couldn't read.
>> This is in federal prison. They couldn't
read.
>> Uhhuh.
>> Oh boy.
>> Here you are playing chess and they
don't even know what checkers is.
>> Yeah. You know, I was standing in the
day room one day. There there's a prison
email system. So, it's not internet, but
it's it's you write an email like to
your wife and it goes to some prison
office and they read it and they say
it's okay and then they send it to your
wife. So, I'm standing at the computer
one day and these two guys start duking
it out, which happened every few months.
What are they duking it out over?
Whether to watch Love and Hip Hop
Atlanta or 101st in Park. I'm totally
serious. They're duking it out like
blood flying and I'm just sitting there.
They're l literally three feet away from
me. I'm doing my email. Well, on the
camera on the security cameras,
they can see in what was called SIS, the
special investigations,
whatever service or these two morons who
just did investigations down there. So,
they see that I'm standing there. Well,
and the thing is is in prison, if
there's a fight, everybody scatters. You
run back to your cell. Why? Because you
do not want to be implicated in a fight.
You'll go straight to solitary and
you'll probably be there for 6 months.
And then if you're lucky, they'll only
transfer you to another prison. They're
not going to punish you further. But I'm
like, "Fuck you. I'm not doing anything.
I'm finishing my email." So, as soon as
the fight ends, I hear Kiryaku,
lieutenant's office, immediately.
I was like, "You dopes." So, I walk down
to the lieutenant's office and I go,
"What?
Why don't you tell us about the fight?"
I go, "What fight? Admit nothing. Deny
everything. Make counter accusations." I
go, "What fight?" "Oh, you're going to
be a wise guy." I go, "I don't know what
you're talking about." What fight? the
fight that was three feet away from you
in the day room.
I said, "There was a fight?"
Very funny. We saw you on the camera
just standing there. I go, "I don't know
what you're talking about." I don't
think there was a fight. Actually, I
think I would have noticed if there was
a fight. Oh, there was a fight. I go,
"Yeah, I think maybe you were fighting.
How do you like that? Why don't you tell
me about the fight since you seem to
know so [__] much about it. And they
were like, "Get the [__] out of my
office." And I was like, "Exactly."
And then I went back and everybody's
like, "You didn't go to solitary." I
said, "They're too [__] stupid to
send me to solitary." I said to the
warden one time, he goes, "You keep
[__] around like this. We're going to
send you to solitary." I said, "Warden,
with all due respect, I have gone nose
tonose with al-Qaeda, with Hezbollah,
with the Iranians, and you want me to be
afraid of you?
Please give me a little credit. I said,
I'm not afraid of your solitary.
And then they never bothered me again.
>> Which tactic was this? Intimidation.
>> Intimidation. There was one that I was
very proud. There were two that I was
very proud of. Um, one was let others do
your dirty work. So, I got called to the
lieutenants office one time because NPR
wanted to do an interview and I had to
sign a a waiver. So they say, "Kiryaku,
lieutenants office." And usually when
you get called to the lieutenant's
office, you're going to solitary. I was
the only one who would get called down
there and come back 15 minutes later
like it was nothing. So um they called
me the lieutenant's office. They said,
"NP called and they want to interview
you. You have to sign this release." So
I signed it. I go back up. In the
meantime, in my housing unit, there was
this guy. He was a serial killer. We
used to call him truck because he had
been a long-distance truck driver. And
what he did was he would stop at truck
stops and he would get prostitutes and
he would have sex with them, but he
wouldn't pay them. He would strangle
them instead. And then he would take
their dead bodies in the truck with him
and just throw them out of the truck in
random places around the western United
States.
Well, one of these girls he strangled,
but he didn't kill her. She lived and
she was able to identify him and he got
caught. They couldn't prove, this is the
days before DNA, they couldn't prove
that he was the killer, but they could
prove that he had raped and attempted to
kill this this 16-year-old girl. So, he
got 20 years. He gets out, he does the
whole 20. He gets out and the cops knew,
like, they really knew he was the serial
killer. So, they set him up and they
would harass him and go to his house and
demand to do an inspection of the house.
And so he got tired of being harassed
and he took a swing at one of the
whatever they are, marshals, I guess,
and he got another 20. So he was in the
second 20 when I was there. For reasons
that I will never understand, this guy
constantly sought my approval. I don't
know why. And to tell you the honest to
God's truth, I was afraid of him. He was
nuts. He he roommed with a child
molester and he hated this child
molester so so much. Not for any
particular reason other than that he was
a child molester that he went to the
commissary one day and bought olive oil
which was on the list of stuff you could
buy. He bought olive oil. He heated it
up in the microwave until it was
boiling.
>> Oh [__]
>> And then he poured it on the guy's face.
Right. It disfigured him permanently.
This kind of person this guy truck was.
So, I didn't know any of this when I
first arrived. And this guy comes up to
me, truck, he says, "So, you're a CIA?"
I go, "Yeah." He goes, "I was CIA." I
go, "I find that hard to believe. Every
CIA guy I knew had teeth."
>> Was he like, "Dude, you don't want to do
that with him. He's nuts." I'm like,
"Whatever." He's like, "I ran a shrimp
boat full of weapons to the Angolan
rebels." I go, "A shrimp boat? Are you
nuts?" I said, "You wouldn't make it
five miles in a shrimp boat. They tip
over. You're going to cross the Atlantic
Ocean." I go, "What the [__] are you
talking about?" And people were like,
"You can't talk to him like that. He's
not. So kill you." But what it did is it
made him want my approval even more. So,
he would say stuff like, "Uh, hey John,
uh, there's a new classic rock station,
1600 a.m. I know you like classic rock.
You should check it out." I'm like,
"Thanks, Truck." "Hey, John, the
Steelers game starts at 1. Uh, I saved
you a seat in the day room." I'm like,
"Oh, thanks, Truck."
So, one day
I'm sitting in the day room.
He's sitting next to me and this guy who
I hated was at the computers and we
called this guy Cat in the Hat because
he had this oddly elongated head. So he
looked just like the Cat in the Hat.
Well, Cat in the Hat wanted to move into
my room at one point into my cell. We
had a free bed. So we had a rule. No
child molesters, right? We're all good.
We called good guys in our room. Like my
bunkmate was the mayor of Cleveland, for
example.
fantastic, awesome guy. Crooked as the
day is long, but he was a natural-born
politician. I loved him. Frank Russo,
God bless him. He's dead now. He had a
heart attack during COVID. So, um, and a
bunch of drug dealers and and a mortgage
fraudster. So, um,
so Cat in the Hat says, "Hey, I see you
have a a bed in there. I I I wanted to
move in." I said, "Well, you got to be
interviewed by everybody in the in the
room." So, he comes to the room for his
interview. This is all very formal, very
serious, you know, in context. I said,
'What's your crime? And he says, 'Murder
for hire.' And I go, oo, I don't think I
like that any better than child
molestation. I said, what what were the
circumstances of murder for hire? And he
says, uh, I used to gamble and I owed
the mafia hundred grand. I couldn't pay
it back, so I took out a $100,000 life
insurance policy on my business partner
and uh and I hired a hitman uh to kill
him.
I said, ' And you got caught? Yeah,
like in a in a minute.
They caught him in a minute. So he
agreed to rat out the hitman. Well, it
turns out the hitman then died of a
heart attack while awaiting trial. So
Cat in the Hat had the benefit of the
deal because he did agree to testify
against the the hitman. They gave him 20
years. Once you get to 10, you can come
to a lower security prison. And I said,
I vote no. Not only are you a murderer,
you're a rat. I said, 'I don't want any
[__] rats in my room. Everybody else
is like, forget it. So this guy hated
me, but he knew I was close to the
Italians. Very close to the Italians. So
I'm sitting there next to truck and this
[__] guy is like three feet away from
me, doesn't know I'm sitting right
behind him. And he says to the guy next
to him, "Did you hear that [__]
Kiryaku got called to the lieutenant's
office?" He goes, "You know why? That
guy's a [__] rat."
And Truck says to me, "Did you hear that
[__] guy? He just called you a rat. I
mean, if you call somebody a rat,
blood's going to be spilled."
And I said, "Yeah." I said, "An hour
ago, I heard him call you a child
molester,
which I totally made up." Without saying
a single word, Truck got up and beat him
almost to death. He was in the hospital
for six weeks.
>> Damn.
>> Truck caught another charge. They added
five more years to the 40 that he
already had. And then Cat in the Hat
after he got out of the hospital was put
in solitary for another couple of
months. And then somebody told him what
I had done. And I ran into him in the
housing unit in it and I said, "Hey, I
got to tell you something. If I ever
hear my name cross your lips ever again,
you're dead. You understand me?" And he
goes, "Yes."
And then that was the end of it. Let
others do your dirty work. There was
this one [__] guy. Let me tell you
this Italian guy, he was engaged to an
A-list Hollywood star, right? She broke
up with him because he was a con man.
This guy never stopped talking. I was in
People magazine again last week. I was
in Variety. I don't know. Nobody cares
if you're in People magazine. And then
he was a degenerate gambler. So he's
borrowing from this guy to pay his debt
to that guy and then borrowing from this
guy to pay that guy. and he's always
broke and he's always ripping people off
and he's always saying, "Oh, when I get
out, you have to come on my yacht and
we're going to go all through the
Mediterranean." I'm like, "You can't buy
[__] ramen noodles. What yacht do you
have?"
His his mother used to come to visit
him. She was pathetic. She would stay in
this $35 a night, you know, roach motel
down the street, and he would sit in the
visiting room and just ball the whole
time his mother was there. Finally, I
said to one of the Italians, I said,
"I've had it with this guy. I'm going to
[__] this guy up." And he's like, "No,
no, no, no, no. Don't do that. You're
going to go to solitary." I said, "No,
no, no. I would never be so crude as to
do it in public." I said, "Watch and
learn."
So,
when you're being released from prison,
they give you a paper called a
merrygoround. And all it is, it's a
paper with your name and your prisoner
ID number. And then it lists all the
offices in the prison and you have to go
on your last day, you have to go and get
a signature for each one. It's
meaningless. It's just to keep you
occupied that last day so you're not out
there settling scores, right?
So one of my cellmates was being
released and I said, "Jose," I said,
"Can I can I borrow your merrygoround
just for an hour?" He's like, "Yeah." So
he gives it to me. I go up to the
library. I make a photo copy of it. I
white out Jose's name and prisoner
number. And then I type in In the book,
I call him Wallace. His name wasn't
Wallace. I I type in Wallace's name and
ID number. And I asked one of the
Italians to steal me a um a uh a laundry
bag, right? So I waited until 5:00 on
Friday and I put the merrygoround and
the laundry bag on Wallace's bed. So,
he's with one of the Gambinos that I
used to hang out with. So, we're in the
room and we're talking and Wallace comes
in. He goes, "Hey guys," we said, "Hey,
Wallace, how you doing?" He walks over
to his bed and he goes,
we go, "What?" He goes, "I'm being
released." I said, "What? What do you
mean?" He goes, "I'm being released." I
must have won my appeal. I said, "Oh my
god, man. Nobody ever wins their
appeals." He goes, "I have to call my
lawyer." He runs to the phone bank.
Well, even fancy New York lawyers leave
by 5:00 on a Friday, right? So, there's
no answer. He goes to the unit manager.
That guy left at 2. Same with the
counselor. Long gone. I said, "Wallace,
let us throw you a party, man. When When
are you going to be released?" He said,
"Munday morning." I said, "Okay, we're
going to we're going to have a big
party, big dinner, all the Italians."
On Saturday, he gave away all his
possessions. [__]
We had a blowout party for him on Sunday
and then on Monday morning we all it was
like a dozen of us. We walked him down
to R&D to uh receiving and discharge.
Now the rest of the story I got from the
cop like the only cop who was nice to me
in receiving and discharge.
Wallace goes in, hands him the
merrygoround and the guy says who the
[__] are you? He goes, "Wallace, what
are you doing here?" He says, "I'm going
home." The guy looks at the merry
ground. He says, "Turn around. You're
under arrest." For what? Attempted
escape.
We could hear him crying.
They cuff him. They take him to
solitary. He was in solitary about six
weeks. And then they sent him to a
prison in Youngsttown, Ohio, where he
served out the remainder of his of his
sentence.
So that night, the number three in the
Banano family, he goes like this.
Very creative. I said, "I told you I was
going to [__] that guy up. He wouldn't
shut his mouth. All he had to do was
shut his mouth and everything would have
been okay." They were like, "Man, you
are a sociopath." What's the lesson
there?
>> The lesson there is I forget which
lesson I put that under. Oh, operate
under the radar. Ne operate under the
radar. Never draw attention to yourself.
Like nobody ever would have known that I
was the bad guy who set that whole thing
in motion. But I knew exactly what I was
doing.
>> What else? These are These are so good.
>> What else? I could tell you how I got
with the Italians
when I first got to the prison.
Um, you talked about how bad the food
was, like criminally bad,
where it's actually marked on the boxes,
not for human consumption, feed use
only. And then they're slapping it on
the plates. I said, and excuse me, you
may even want to edit this out. I said
to one of the guards, I said, "I've
eaten ass that tasted better than this."
>> That's how bad it was.
Sorry,
>> I'm leaving that.
>> Never actually said that out loud
before.
>> That's how bad it was. It was dangerous.
>> And so,
>> did you supplement with commissary food?
>> That's what you had to do. But it it got
even better, though. It wasn't just John
going to commissary and making stuff.
When I first arrived on my very first
day, as they're processing me in, the
only thing the cops, it's that same
friendly cop that told me about Wallace,
the only thing he said to me was, "If
someone comes into your cell uninvited,
that's an act of aggression." And I go,
"Great. Thank you. Great. I've been here
40 minutes and I'm going to have my ass
kicked. Terrific."
So, I'm there like two hours and these
two guys come in. One has a swastika
tattoo that takes up his entire neck and
comes up onto his face and the other
guy, little fat guy, he has [__] you
tattooed on his eyelids. So every time
he blinks it says [__] you. So I jump
up. I go, "What do you want?" Right? And
one of them goes, "Take it easy." The
Nazi guy, "Take it easy." He goes, I'm
standing there like this. He goes, "Are
you the new guy?" I go, "Yeah." He goes,
"Are you a fag?" I said, "No, I'm not a
[__] Are you a rat?" I said, "No, I'm
not a rat. I didn't have anybody else in
my case." And he goes, "You a cho?" I
go, "I don't know what that means." He
goes,
he goes, "Chomo, child molester." I
said, "No, I'm not a [__] child
molester." He goes, "Okay, you can sit
with the Aryans in the cafeteria." And I
go, "Oh,
okay." And I'm thinking, "So, I'm with
the Aryans now. Great. I've watched Oz.
I know how this plays out. So, three,
four days later, this black guy comes
in. This like totally rippling muscle,
like the most perfect example of a human
being I've ever seen in my life. And I
jump up and I'm thinking, I'm not going
to last two minutes with this guy. I go,
"What do you want?" He's got a
newspaper, this little newspaper, and he
very gingerly hands it to me and he
says, "Are you the CIA man?" And I go,
"Yeah." And he says,"Reverend Farrakhan
says,"You're a hero of the Muslim
people." I said, 'Oh.' And I look at the
newspaper and it's like, Farrakhan says,
"Kiryaku, hero of the Muslim people."
Cuz I was anti-torrture.
And he said, "I just want to tell you
you're not going to have any problems
with us." I said, "Okay, thank you." And
he walks out. Never spoke to him again.
They don't talk to the white devil. Like
they'll tell you, "I don't talk to the
white devil." So there's no
conversation, no relationship there.
Four members, four of my cellmates were
members of um of Mexican cartels. And so
one of them said to me one day, "Are you
educated?" And I said, "Yeah." He said,
"Would you write my appeal?" I said,
"I'm not a lawyer." "Yeah, but you're
educated." I go, "Yeah." I said, "Sure.
I'm probably smarter than half the
lawyers out there. Sure, I'll write your
appeal. Give me your paperwork. I'll
figure it out." This guy was as guilty
as the day is long. had like 20 tons of
cocaine in a warehouse and he opens fire
on the DEA and they open fire on him. He
even showed me his bullet wound scars.
Like he's guilty guilty. So I write the
appeal. The appeals denied, but he told
all the other Mexicans that I wrote the
appeal and I didn't charge him anything.
He like he offered me the currency is
bags of uh mackerel because they cost
exactly $1 or books of stamps because at
the time they cost $8. And I said, "No,
no. I I got people on the outside. They
they take care of me. I don't need any
money." So he told all the Mexicans, and
they were like, "Okay, well, he's he's
okay then." So directly across the hall
from me was the number three in the
Banano family, um, Senior Cabo. And I
used to give him my New York Times. He'd
give me his New York Post. We'd watch
football together. And he said to me one
day, "Let me ask you a question. Why do
you sit with those Nazi retards in the
cafeteria?
And I said, I don't know. My first day
they told me to sit with them. He goes,
from today you're with the Italians.
And I said, great.
>> You said you met with them outside of
prison two weeks ago. Are you getting
followed by the feds?
>> This is what I say to the feds.
>> This they follow you.
>> They stopped. I got out in 2015. They
stopped by 2017.
>> They spent two years.
>> Yeah. A buddy of mine from the CIA
called me one day and he said, "Hey, you
want to you want to go out for a pizza?"
I said, "Yeah, I'd love to see you." He
lived in Restston, Virginia, which is it
was far. It was about 15 miles from my
place. So, listen, I was a surveillance
instructor at the CIA. So, immediately I
see there are three cars on me. How How
quick?
>> Oh, within three blocks.
Listen, a [__] snow plow is not going
to follow me through my neighborhood
like this.
>> A snowplow is following you. snow plow
on the front. I'm like, "Seriously, you
guys, you morons. This is how the FBI
is. They have their heads up their asses
half the time." So, I I go to the pizza
place and um and I go in, I see my
buddy, big hug, and I said I said, "Did
you spot surveillance on the way over
here?" He said, "Absolutely not." I
said, "Well, I sure did." And he's like,
"Are they still doing that?" And I said,
"Yes." So, we sat and ate our pizza and
I drove home and I'm like, "Fuck you
guys for wasting your whole day of the
taxpayers's money."
>> How did you spot it? How do you spot the
surveillance
>> when you first pull out?
Nine times out of 10, you're going to
pull out from your house, right? Unless
you're, you know, at your office, but
most of the time in the morning, you're
at you're at the house. So, if I'm going
to go to rest in, I'm going to need to
take a highway for the most part to get
to rest in. But to get to the highway, I
have to go through my neighborhood. And
so, it's going to be about two miles to
get to the highway. Well, I know all the
shortcuts, so I'm not going straight to
the highway. And these idiots don't know
I'm going to get a pizza and rested.
They're like, "Oh, he's going to go leak
secrets to someone." So, they're on me.
And they don't want to risk losing me
because they know I'm trained in counter
surveillance.
And so it's like a Volkswagen Jetta, a
freaking snow plow, which I'll never
forget, and then some other car, I don't
remember what it was. And so I just drag
them like this all the way to Boston.
>> The longer way,
>> the longer way. And then I get on the
highway and I go to Reston. And I I
dragged all three of them with me all
the way to Reston.
>> Like nice nice tap on their spend the
taxpayers money.
>> Did you tap on their window when you
left the pizza place? Yeah, I did that
once in in 2012. In the summer of 2012,
George Washington University hired me to
do a surveillance and surveillance
detection course.
>> That's when you went to school, too,
right?
>> Yeah. So, I had a dozen students and on
our very first day, I broke down what a
surveillance detection route is and how
you put one together. So, I said, "What
we're going to do to start off is we're
going to walk through what would
normally be a 2-hour surveillance
detection route. It's going to take us
about an hour and a half because we're
not going to actually stop at the
stops." So, we leave from the dormatory.
We go up 20th Street to a bookstore, a
combination bookstore cafe in uh Dupont
Circle.
The reason I like this bookstore cafe is
because you can buy a book, have a
coffee, and there's a back door. So, you
go in the front door, you do your thing,
you leave the back door, it puts you in
a neighborhood, then you loop around to
see who comes through the building with
you, and then I want to go to Georgetown
from there. Well, the only way to get to
Georgetown is across what's called the
Pea Street Bridge because there's Rock
Creek that separates Dupont Circle from
Georgetown. It's it's a chasm. So, the
bridge is like 500 feet above the creek.
Well, the only way to get from one
neighborhood to the other is across this
little bridge. So, if you're under
surveillance, they have to follow you
over the bridge.
So,
I said to these kids, they're all like
18, they've just started college. I
said, "This is gonna sound crazy, but I
believe we are actually under
surveillance." I said, "I don't know if
you guys noticed, but there's a woman
and a man who followed us into the cafe
and out the back and they looped around
and came to the bridge. Now, we've
crossed the bridge and there's a woman
sitting alone in a car reading a
newspaper, which never ever happens in
real life, only in the movies. So, I
said, "What you would do is you would
jot down descriptions of the two who are
on foot and jot down the license plate
number of this one and the description
of her and a description of the car."
Just then, my cell phone rings and it's
my lawyer. He said, "I just got a
strange call from the FBI. They said
that you are acting very suspiciously as
if you are doing a surveillance
detection route. And I said, tell these
retards at the FBI that I am doing a
surveillance detection route and that a
group of 18-year-olds on their first
surveillance outing caught them.
the vaunted FBI
that they're so great at what they do. A
bunch of 18-year-old kids spotted their
surveillance. So, I said, "Tell them I'm
teaching a surveillance class and to
mind their business." And so, they broke
off.
>> You got recruited out of George
Washington.
>> My my uh grad school adviser was
actually undercover as a grad school
adviser. He was a CIA officer acting as
what was then called a spotter looking
for people who would fit into the CIA
culture and he thought I would fit in.
>> What did he notice about you?
>> Uh he had assigned us a paper
uh where we had to shadow our bosses and
write a psychological profile of our
bosses. I was working at the United Food
and Commercial Workers Union at the
time. And my boss was this mean, foul,
old school union organizer. I was
actually a little bit afraid of him. And
halfway through the week, we got into an
argument, quite a bad argument, and I
called him a racist, which he was. He
was just a disgusting human being. And
he got so mad, he baldled up his fist
and he set his stance. And I put my
hands up like, "Dang, I went too far
this time." I put my hands up and he
goes, "My penis is bigger than yours."
And I said, "What?" He goes, "My penis
is bigger than yours." I said, "You know
what? You're nuts." And I quit and I
walked out. So I went back to my dorm. I
wrote my paper. I said, "He's a
sociopath with psychopathic and possibly
violent tendencies." And I footnoted the
daylights out of it. And you know, this
this shrink said that and this shrink
said this, and he fits the pattern. So I
got the um paper back. back a week
later, I got an A and the professor
wrote in the margin, "Please see me
after class." And so I went to see him
and he's like, "Look, I'm not really a
professor here and I think you would
make a good CIA officer. What do you
say?" And I said, "Yeah, talking to you
today, even before the show and during
the show, one thing that resonated with
me or just I can kind of pick up from
our conversations is the truth is really
important to you."
>> Oh my god, there's nothing as important
as the truth. Nothing. even when it's a
hideous truth. Right? Listen, it it's my
own experience. I'm 61 now. I'm not a
kid anymore, but it's my experience in
life that the truth always comes out.
So, own it. Listen, you and I can
disagree on torture, right? Reasonable
people can disagree
about what constitutes torture.
But if you make a decision that you want
to do these different things to people,
then own it. Don't pretend that it's not
happening. Own it because the truth's
going to come out. I said way back in
2012 when I was arrested, I said the
reason why
the pro-torrture people at the CIA are
doubling down on torture is because they
know deep down that they're wrong.
Right? We all know deep in our gut the
difference between right and wrong. And
they know that when they die and their
orbituaries are written, it's going to
say that they were torturers.
And so they think that if they repeat
the lie over and over and over again
that the American people will finally
come over to their their line of
thinking. And that's just not going to
be the case because Americans know that
it's wrong.
What was the moment in your career that
you just knew that you had to come out
with the information knowing the
consequences you're going to face?
>> Well, to tell you the truth, I really
believed for a long time that somebody
else would come out and say something,
right? Because there were a lot of
people listen in that position where I
told you I had access to everything. I'm
seeing the reporting cables from the
secret prisons and it's like the
secretary walked in while we were
torturing this guy and she fainted and
now she wants to come home. That's a
career-ending move. It's called a
curtailment. You're curtailing your
assignment. You will never be promoted
again if you curtail an assignment. We
had doctors saying, "I quit. I took a
hypocratic oath to first do no harm. And
you want me to revive this guy just so
you can torture him more? I quit. So I
thought, well, I'm obviously not the
only person who opposes torture. One of
these people, one of them is going to
pick up the phone and call the
Washington Post. And then none of them
did. And then finally in 2007, Brian
Ross from ABC News called me. I'd never
met him before. He said, "I have a
source who says you tortured Abu Zuba."
I said, "Absolutely not true. I was the
only person who was kind to Abu Zuba."
Well, you're welcome to come on the show
and defend yourself. He said,
I said, "I'll think about it." And I
wasn't going to do it. But then later
that week, the president, George W.
Bush, gave a press conference in which
he looked right in the camera and he
goes, "We do not torture." I said to my
wife, "He's a bald-faced liar. He is
looking the American people in the eye
and he's lying to every one of us." And
then two more days later, it was a
Friday, he was walking, he came out of
the South Portico of the White House and
he was walking to the to the helicopter,
Marine One, to go to Camp David for the
weekend. and a reporter shouted a
question about torture and he stopped
and he said, "Well, if there is torture,
it's because of a rogue CIA officer and
I said to my wife,
Brian Ross' source is at the White House
and they're going to try to pin this on
me." So, I called him and I said, "I'll
give you your interview." And I decided,
you know what?
In for a penny, in for a pound. Whatever
he asks me, I'm just going to tell the
truth. And that's exactly what I did.
>> On your website, you have one phrase
that caught my attention, and that says,
"Truth matters.
What is the one thing you wish people
understood about you?"
>> I mean, I I could give you kind of a
flippant answer. I'll give you both a
real answer and a flippant answer. There
is literally nothing that I hate more
that when I read in the comment section
of a podcast that I've done, once CIA,
always CIA, that is the most
intellectually lazy and [__] moronic
thing a person could possibly say. I
used to respond to that by saying, "Oh,
okay. I'll tell Ed Snowden and Ray
McGovern and the sons of Philip Agy that
you think they're still in the CIA, you
[__] I hate that. That's not really
what matters.
What matters is
in the CIA's culture,
they train us to believe that everything
in life is a shade of gray.
And that's just not true. Some things
are black and white. they're right or
wrong. And like I said to you earlier,
we know in in our guts what's right and
what's wrong. The question then is do we
do what's right? Even if there's a
personal cost and I would say we have to
do what's right. Let me let me give you
another example. I I use this example
and this is not a real life example. I
made this up but I I give this example
at college campuses when I speak. Let's
say that you are a CIA case officer and
you've recruited an agent who is a
bonafide terrorist, an honest to god
penetration of a major terrorist
organization, and you meet with him once
a month in a in a hotel somewhere in the
Middle East, doesn't matter where.
Everything this guy has given you has
proved to be true. He's saved American
lives. So you fly out one month to meet
with him and he says to you
everything I've given you has been true.
So tonight you're going to do something
for me. You're going to go out and get
me a prostitute. And if you don't, I'm
not talking to you anymore. So I said,
"Give me a show of hands. How many would
get him the prostitute?" And usually
about 80% will put their hands up. And I
say, "Yeah, you would. It's ugly. It's
dirty. It's gross. But yeah, you'd get
him the prostitute. What if he tells you
he wants a child prostitute?"
And usually people kind of look around
and then about 10% kind of gingerly put
their hands up and I say, "Absolutely
not. Not under any circumstances." See,
but this is the this is the problem.
There's no class at the CIA in ethics.
There's not going to be somebody at
headquarters to say, "Now, now, John,
you don't get him the child prostitute.
That's the wrong thing to do." That that
person doesn't exist. You have to know
in your heart what's right and wrong.
So, you go into this job with your own
set of moral values. They're not going
to teach it to you. And sometimes
everybody in your chain of command is
doing the wrong thing. That's when you
have to stand up. So the truth always
matters and the truth will always come
out. Be on the right side of it. That's
what I'd like people to know.